Good evening or good night wherever you are,
傍晚好，晚上好，无论你在哪里，
let's get started.
我们开始吧。
So today, I wanna talk a little bit about chain replication,
今天，我想谈谈链式复制，
the paper aside for today from 2004,
今天的论文来自 2004 ，
before diving into the paper,
在深入研究这篇论文之前，
a couple quick logistic things I just want to remind you of,
我想提醒你几件后勤上的事，
one is we have a quiz on Thursday,
一是我们周四有个测验，
and you know the instructions of topics that actually being covered all the quiz
测验的所有主题说明
are on the schedule page,
都在课程表页面上，
we'll try to send out an announcement of Piazza for more details
我们会在 Piazza 上发布公告，包含更多细节，
about exactly how we'll do the quiz,
关于我们怎么做测验，
it's going to be in grade scope,
它将在[年级范围]内，
and it's basically during class hours 80 minutes,
是在上课时间 80 分钟，
and more details to follow.
以及后续更多细节。
The second you know I want to remind people of is projects,
第二个我想提醒大家的是项目，
if you'd like to do a project instead of lab 4,
如果你想做一个项目而不是实验 4 ，
then you can do so,
那么你可以这么做，
but you should submit a proposal for a project,
但你应该提交一份项目建议书，
and use a couple paragraphs to through the submission website,
使用几个段落，通过提交网站提交，
so that we can give you feedback,
这样我们就可以给你反馈，
and to tell you what this project actually appropriate for a final project in 6.824,
告诉你这个项目是否适合 6.824 的期末项目，
if you're just planning to lab 4,
如果你只是计划去做实验 4 ，
there's absolutely nothing you have to do at all.
你不需要做任何事情。
Any questions about these two logistical points?
对这两个[后勤点]，有什么问题吗？
Okay, then, let me move on to one other point,
好的，那么，让我转移到另一点，
I wanted to bring up,
我想提出，
which is the sort of correction from a lecture a little while ago,
就是之前课程的正确性，
we, we walked through the Go code
我们演练了 Go 代码
for the raft implementation of 2a 2b that I had,
关于我的 raft 实现 2a 2b ，
and we talked a little bit about the go defer statement,
我们谈了关于 Go defer 语句的事情，
and I mentioned that,
我提到过，
you can actually have the defer statement inside of a base block,
你可以将 defer 语句放在基本块中，
and that is correct,
这是正确的，
and I think maybe it was Felipe who asked the question,
我认为可能是 Felipe 提出了这个问题，
what is exactly when is that get executed
这个到底是什么时候执行的，
and I answered that question incorrectly,
我对这个问题的回答有误，
you know the defer statement that gets executed
defer 语句被执行
at the point that gets return out of the function,
在从函数返回时，
not in return out of the base block,
而不是在基础块返回的时候，
and so that my apologizes that caused any confusion.
所以，我对任何引起的疑惑表示抱歉。
Any questions about the that clarification?
对于这个澄清，有什么问题吗？
Okay?
好的？
Good, there's sort of two topics
好的，有两个主题，
and really talk to technical talks,
都是技术讨论，
I want to talk about today is the zookeeper locks,
今天我想谈的是 zookeeper 的锁，
which I didn't get to finish the last time,
上次我没能完成，
and then I'll talk about chain replication.
然后我将讨论链式复制。
Okay?
好的？
So both for chain replication and zookeeper,
对于链式复制和 zookeeper 来说，
you know we're sort of still in the same context as before,
我们仍然处在和以前一样的环境中，
namely we're doing you know replicated state machine.
也就是，我们在做复制状态机。
And you know just a usual diagram,
这是一张常见的图，
you know we have servers,
我们有服务器，
you know that runs on some replication libraries, like ZAB or Raft,
它运行一些复制库，比如 ZAB 或 Raft ，
we have clients talking to the servers,
我们有客户端与服务器交互，
for example in the case of zookeeper,
例如在 zookeeper 的情况中，
might actually send to create call,
可能发送 create 调用，
you know zookeeper internally how some states, you know some znodes,
zookeeper 内部有一些状态，一些 znode ，
you know that are hanging off in a form of tree,
它们是以树的形式存在的，
and so when an operation comes in,
所以，当一个操作进来时，
you know zookeeper you know forwards that operation basically to the Raft ZAB library,
zookeeper 把这个操作转发给 ZAB 库，
it does some chatting back and forth,
它会来回聊天，
and to get a majority of the servers
为了获得服务器的大多数，
to accept you know that command,
为了接受那个命令，
and then at some point,
然后在某个时刻，
you know once it's accepted, it comes out,
一旦它被接受，它出来了，
the servers applies the operation,
服务器应用了操作，
and sends a response back to the client,
并将响应发送回客户端，
so the standard story of replicated state machine,
所以这是复制状态机的标准故事，
if you start,
如果你启动，
all the replicated state machine starting the same state,
所有复制状态机都会以相同的状态启动，
you apply the same operation in the same order,
你以相同的顺序应用相同的操作，
then you will end up in the same state,
然后你就会以同样的状态结束，
and so any of the machines can take over if necessary.
所以，如果有必要，任何一台机器都可以接管。
Now, one of the things that was cool, about interesting, about zookeeper is that,
现在，关于 zookeeper 有趣的事情之一是，
you know read operations can be served for any servers,
读操作可有由任何服务器提供，
for any of the peers or any of the one of the servers,
对于任何节点或任何一个服务器，
and this allows zookeeper to extremely high performance,
这使得 zookeeper 拥有极高的性能，
because you can actually scale the number of read operations with the number of servers,
因为你可以通过扩展服务器的数量来扩展读操作的数量，
as a flip side of that,
作为它的另一面，
you know zookeeper actually gave up,
zookeeper 放弃了，
on that particular scenario,
在特定场景下，
gave up on linearizability.
放弃了线性一致性。
Because we know from for example in Raft,
因为我们知道，比如在 Raft 中，
we can't actually arbitrary server read from any server,
我们不能从任何服务器进行读取，
because I have not seen the latest update yet,
因为我还没有看到最新的更新，
and so in case of zookeeper,
所以在 zookeeper 的情况下，
that is a [],
这是[]，
and, and so read operations are not you know,
读操作不是，
or the operation zookeeper defines don't provide a linearizable interface.
或者 zookeeper 定义的操作不提供线性化的接口。
But nevertheless you know we saw that actually is,
尽管如此，我们看到是，
it provides a slightly different sort of correctness guarantee that linearizability,
它提供了一种与线性一致性略微不同的正确性保证，
and that actually correctness guarantee is useful,
而且这种正确性保证是有用的，
and useful enough to be able to write actually programs,
并且足够有用，能够编写实际的程序，
and the particular set of programs that you know zookeeper was you know focusing on is,
zookeeper 所关注的特定程序是，
these what they call configuration or coordination programs.
他们称为配置或协调程序。
And so the thing to think about it,
所以想一想这件事，
there's a lot of systems that we looked at in the past,
过去我们看到了很多系统，
they typically have some replication story,
它们通常有一些复制的故事，
and they have coordinator master that sort of coordinates the the group,
它们有 coordinator master 用来协调组，
and zookeeper really intended you know for as a service,
zookeeper 想要的是作为一个服务，
for that kind of you know master or coordinator role,
对于那种 master 或 coordinator 的角色，
and it provides a bunch of primitives you know to make that doable,
它提供了一系列原语来实现这一点，
and the two the you know we talked a little bit about atomic increment last week,
我们上周讨论了原子增加，
and with some the other service
和一些其他服务，
and want to finish off you know talking about locks.
想通过谈论锁来结束。
One, because there were a lot of questions about it,
第一，因为有很多关于它的问题，
and two, actually is quite interesting,
第二，它是非常有趣的，
and there's sort of two different lock in implementation.
这里有两种不同的锁实现。
And first I want to talk about the simple one,
首先我想谈谈简单的那个，
namely where, let me write down the pseudo code,
让我写下伪代码，
then we can talk about it again a little bit in detail,
然后我们可以谈谈细节，
so the pseudo code for the lock was something like this,
所以锁的伪代码是像这样，
you know acquire, in an infinite loop,
acquire ，在一个无限循环中，
you know try to create the lock file,
试着创建锁文件，
name lf, and set ephemeral to true,
命名为 lf ，并将 ephmeral 设置为 true ，
and we'll talk about that in a second why.
我们稍后会讨论为什么。
You know if the create succeeds,
如果创建成功，
then you know the that process,
然后那个进程，
where the client was the first one to create that file,
第一个创建文件的客户端，
and basically successfully gets the lock
成功地获得了锁
and so it breaks out of the for loop and returns.
所以，它打破 for 循环并返回。
If the client did not,
如果客户端没有，
you know be able to create a file,
创建一个文件，
then it calles exists,
然后它调用 exists ，
and the call exists is not really for you know see if it exists or not,
调用 exists 并不是为了看它是否存在，
because you know it doesn't exist,
因为它并不存在，
basically set a watch,
就是设置一个 watch ，
and the idea is that you know the watch will go off,
想法是， watch 会触发，
if actually the file disappears,
如果文件消失了，
and if it disappears,
如果它消失了，
then you know the client will get a notification,
客户端会收到通知，
so basically we're going to be doing here is
所以我们在这里要做的是
just wait for that notification.
等待通知。
So that's sort of the acquire operation,
所以这是 acquire 操作，
then the release is very simple.
然后 release 就很简单了。
The release actually is that does nothing else
release 基本上不做任何其他事情，
than sending the delete operation to the zookeeper service,
只是发送 delete 操作到 zookeeper 服务，
you know for the for the lock file,
对于锁文件来说，
so lf in this case.
在这种情况下是 lf 。
And so what does that do,
那么这是做什么，
well if the delete you know sent to the zookeeper service,
如果 delete 发送给 zookeeper 服务，
you know the zookeeper service perform delete operation,
zookeeper 服务执行 delete 操作，
that will actually, that that make the file would go away,
这将会让文件消失，
that will fire to watch,
会通知 watch ，
and so every client that actually is waiting,
所以每个在等待的客户端，
you know for the notification,
对于通知，
will get a notification,
将会收到一条通知，
and then they go retry,
然后它们会去重试，
and you know one of them will be successful in the retry,
它们中的一个将在重试中成功，
will get the lock file or create a lock file,
将获取锁文件或创建锁文件，
and then proceed,
然后继续，
and then the others one go back into there,
然后其他的又回到那里，
call exists and going to wait for notification.
调用 exists 并等待通知。
And the zookeeper semantics you know good enough,
zookeeper 语义足够好，
you know the strong the linearizability for write operations,
对写操作的线性一致性，
plus you know the rules for when notifications go off
加上通知发出的规则，
are strong enough, that basically this actually implements a [] lock,
足够强，来实现一个[]锁，
where only one client,
只有一个客户端，
if there are many clients at the same time trying to get the lock,
如果同时有多个客户端试图获取锁，
only one will get it.
只有一个会得到它。
And when the release is done
当 release 完成时，
or when the file has been deleted,
或者当文件被删除时，
only one in the next round will get it.
在下一轮中只有一个能拿到它。
So that's sort of cool,
所以这有点酷，
and it's interesting,
它是有趣的，
that you could build you know sort of sort of the foundational primitive
你可以构建某种基础原语，
on using the primitives that the zookeeper offers.
使用 zookeeper 提供的原语。
And you see here, both the role,
你看这两个角色，
of the you know the the watch and then there's the second role for the ephemeral,
watch 和第二个角色 ephemeral ，
you know the ephemeral is there,
ephemeral 在这里，
because, what happens if a client fails or crash,
因为，如果客户端失败或崩溃，
before it calls release,
在它调用 release 之前，
and the semantics of the ephemeral files,
ephemeral 文件的语义，
that zookeeper service will,
zookeeper 服务将会，
if it decides that the client has crashed,
如果它确定客户端已经崩溃，
it will do the operation,
它会执行操作，
it will remove the file on behalf of the client,
它将删除代表客户端的文件，
so even if the client fails or crashes,
所以，即使客户端出现故障或崩溃，
zookeeper service the [site],
zookeeper 服务[]，
at some point the client is down,
某个时刻，客户端掉线，
and that will remove the file lock f,
这将删除文件锁 f ，
which will cause notifications to be sent
这将导致发送通知
to other clients actually are waiting for it.
到等待它的其他客户端。
So, it's a cool set of primitives
所以，这是一组很酷的原语，
to build powerful abstraction that can be useful in applications.
构建在应用程序中有用的强大[抽象]。
One downside of this particular implementation is that,
这个实现的一个缺点是，
it has what's called a herding effect,
它具有所谓的羊群效应，
namely you know let's say you have a thousand clients,
也就是说，假设你有一千个客户端，
you know want to go grab the lock file or make the lock file,
想要获取锁文件或创建锁文件，
acquire the lock,
获取锁，
you know one is going to succeed,
一个会成功，
and 999 are going to call exists and wait for notification,
999 将调用 exists 并等待通知，
then when the first client deletes the file or releases the file lock,
然后当第一个客户端删除文件或释放文件锁时，
999 are going to try to actually acquire the lock,
999 将尝试获取锁，
and of course only one is going to succeed,
当然，只有一个会成功，
and 998 are going to be sitting for a notification,
998 将会等待通知，
but you know the this,
但你知道这个，
you know every sort of random disappearance,
每一个随机消失，
a huge amount of traffic,
会产生巨大的流量，
and you know basically bombarding you know the zookeeper server,
基本上就是轰炸 zookeeper 服务器，
999 to try to do it again,
999 尝试重新执行，
you know all but one are are gonna fail.
除了一个，所有都会失败。
And so that's a little bit of undesirable property, this herding effect,
所以这是不受欢迎的性质，这种羊群效应，
and it's a real problem in practice,
这在实践中是一个真正的问题，
you know move on a small scale multi-core machines
在小规模的多核机器上移动，
as well as of course setting like this,
当然还有像这样的设置，
where network messages are not free.
网络消息不是免费的。
So it's interesting that, actually zookeeper provides enough primitives,
所以，有趣的是， zookeeper 提供了足够的原语，
that you could actually do quite a bit better,
你可以做得更好，
and you can actually build a lock,
你可以创建一个锁，
that doesn't have suffered from the herding effect.
不会受到羊群效应的影响。
So a better lock,
所以更好的锁，
and it's very interesting,
它是非常有趣的，
let me a pull out the pseudo code for this,
让我找出这个的伪代码，
which is in the paper,
在论文中，
so we can look at it,
这样我们就能看到它了，
and discuss you know why you know this lock is better,
并讨论为什么这个锁更好，
and particularly what we'll see is that this lock is better,
我们看到的是这个锁更好，
because basically there's no, there's no retry,
因为这里没有重试，
where all clients that didn't succeed getting the lock will retry to try to get,
所有未成功获取锁的客户端都将重试获取，
instead you know basically the all the clients are sort of for a line,
相反，所有的客户端都排成一条线，
and they get the lock one by one.
它们可以一个接一个地获取锁。
And the way you know that you can program that using zookeeper's primitives
你可以 zookeeper 原语编程的方式，
as in this particular pseudo code.
像这个伪代码一样。
And there are a couple differences that compared to the previous one,
这与上一个有些不同，
first of all, the,
首先，这个，
there's an additional flag you know pass to create, namely SEQUENTIAL,
这有一个额外的传递给 create 的标志，即 SEQUENTIAL ，
which basically means that,
这意味着，
as these files are created,
当创建这些文件时，
the lock file is created,
锁文件被创建，
but it will be created as, the first one, it will be lock-0,
但它将被创建为，第一个将是 lock-0 ，
then the next one will be lock-1, etc.
下一个将是 lock-1 ，依此类推。
So we have like a thousand clients
所以，我们有一千个客户端
rushing you know to the service to actually try to acquire to lock,
争先恐后地到服务上试图获取锁，
basically a thousand files will be created,
基本上会创建一千个文件，
all numbered from 0 to 999.
所有的数字是从 0 到 999 。
Then, so.
然后，那么。
So, I'll succeed creating a file,
所以，我将成功创建一个文件，
the creator returns actually the number that that you got,
创建者返回你得到的数字，
so if the client 0,
所以如果客户端 0 ，
if the first client gets you know lock, creates lock-0,
如果第一个客户端创建了 lock-0 ，
then it will get 0 back,
那么它将获得 0 ，
and the second will get 1 back, etc, etc.
第二个将得到 1 ，依此类推。
Then you know the pseudo code basically ask
然后伪代码要求，
you know to get all the children in that directory
获取这个目录中的所有子项，
you know which you know these files are created,
那些文件被创建的，
and so in this case,
所以在这种情况下，
maybe that would be a thousand children and thousand znodes,
可能有一千个子节点，一千个 znode ，
and then you can just look at the n,
然后你可以查看 n ，
and see if your n,
看看你的 n ，
in this case, 0 is the lowest znode to see,
在这种情况下， 0 是要查看的最小 znode ，
and if that's the case, that means you got the lock.
如果是这样的话，就意味着你拿到了锁。
And so that makes total sense,
所以这完全有道理，
but the first line gets actually 0 back,
第一行得到了 0 ，
all the other clients have a higher number,
所有其他客户端都有更高的数字，
because they're sequentially numbered,
因为它们是按顺序编号的，
and so the first client will succeed in getting it,
所以，第一个客户端将成功地获得它，
and all the other ones, what they're gonna do is,
而所有其他，它们要做的是，
they're going to look at,
它们会查看，
they're going to find the p,
它们会找到 p ，
you know the number that is right in front of there,
这个数字正好在它前面，
so for example if this is client,
例如，如果这是客户端，
that got back you know lock-10,
它获得 lock-10 ，
it's going to look you know for znode 9 you know lock-9,
它将查找 znode 9 ， lock-9 ，
and basically put a watch on that file,
在那个文件上放一个 watch ，
so this means that every client will have a watch basically on its predecessor,
这意味着每个客户端都有一个 watch 在它的前一个节点，
so it goes to see that's all the clients form a line,
所以所有的客户都排成一条线，
and and then you know the client just gonna wait for that notification to go off.
然后，客户端等待通知发出。
And so that means for example when client 0 you know we got 0 back,
这意味着，例如，当客户端 0 得到 0 ，
you know releases the lock,
释放锁，
it will delete n,
它将删除 n ，
this will get a notification to go off for the file one,
文件 1 将收到通知发出，
and so the client is actually waiting for that particular notification,
所以，客户端正在等待该通知，
then will run,
然后运行，
but it's the only one that runs,
但它是唯一可以运行的，
and a it will succeed.
而且它会成功。
And so here we see,
所以我们在这里看到，
you know this is sometimes easier type of locks, called ticket locks,
这有时是一种更简单的锁，称为标签锁，
in multi-core programming,
在多核编程中，
if you're familiar with them,
如果你对它们很熟悉，
and they are sort of the same same idea of ticket locks,
它们在某种程度上与标签锁是相同的想法，
actually you're building into this, using zookeeper primitives.
你将使用 zookeeper 原语构建这个。
Again, what is interesting about it is that,
再说一次，有趣的是，
you know these primitives are powerful enough,
这些原语足够强大，
that you can actually build these kind of locks.
你可以创建这种锁。
Any questions about this?
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
Okay, I want to make one more comment you know about the these locks,
好的，关于这些锁，我想再说一句，
before moving onto chain replication.
在进入链式复制之前。
We have a question in the chat.
我们在聊天中有一个问题。
Yeah, okay, what's the question in chat?
好的，聊天中的问题是什么？
What is the watch for on line 4?
第 4 行的 watch 是做什么的？
Good, go back, on this one line 4?
好的，回去，在这个第 4 行吗？
Yeah, I think that's the question.
是的，我想这就是问题。
Yeah, well, that watch my comment,
好的，这个 watch ，我的注释，
the watch actually should go with you know line 5,
这个 watch 应该在第 5 行，
so there's no watch on line 4, right,
所以在第 4 行没有 watch ，
line 4 just finds p, you know the numbers right before your n,
第 4 行只是查找 p ，你的 n 之前的数字，
if that doesn't answer the question,
如果这没有回答问题，
please, if you come back later and that's fine.
你可以晚点再提问，也可以。
Actually, I have another question.
事实上，我还有一个问题。
Yeah.
嗯。
This is going actually I think back a few slides,
我想回退几张幻灯片，
but how does zookeeper determine that a client has failed,
但是 zookeeper 如何确定客户失败，
and thus release the ephemeral lock,
从而释放 ephemeral 锁，
like often, it's just like partitions for a moment.
比如通常只是短暂出现分区。
Yeah, so, well, yeah so that could happen,
是的，所以这是可能的，
so the client might actually,
所以客户端可能会，
so the client has a session right with the zookeeper service,
客户端有一个与 zookeeper 服务交互的 session ，
and the client needs to,
客户端需要，
actually the zookeeper and client basically sends heartbeats to each other,
zookeeper 和客户端互相发送心跳，
if zookeeper service doesn't hear from a client for a little while,
如果 zookeeper 服务一段时间没有收到客户端的心跳，
then it's just desides that client is down and close the session.
然后，它决定客户端掉线并关闭会话。
And so the client is trying to send messages on the session,
客户端尝试在会话上发送消息，
but the session is just closed, is gone,
但是会话已经关闭，已经消失，
and any files that were created in the,
任何被创建的文件，
ephemeral files that were created during that session are basically deleted,
这个会话期间创建的 ephemeral 文件会被删除，
and so if the network reconvenes or [],
如果网络恢复，
then the client will try to send messages over that session,
客户端尝试通过那个 session 发送消息，
and basically zookeeper service say like that session doesn't exist anymore,
zookeeper 服务会说那个 session 已经不存在了，
you gotta retry or restart a new session.
你必须重试或重新开始一个新的 session 。
Got it, thank you.
知道了，谢谢。
Okay good, so there's one important point about this,
好的，有一点很重要，
I'll call zlocks, where zookeeper locks,
我称为  zlock ， zookeeper 锁，
and that is they're not the same or have similar semantics,
它们并不相同或具有相似的语义，
like the locks that you were using or Go locks or mutex.
你正在使用的锁， Go 锁或 mutex 。
And it's sort of an important point to realize,
这是一个需要注意的重要问题，
you know even though they're different,
即使它们不同，
we'll see in a second, they're still useful,
我们一会儿就会知道，它们仍然很有用，
but they're not as strong as sort of the Go locks,
但它们不像 Go 锁那样强，
in particular the case is that is interesting is,
尤其是有趣的是，
like when the lock holder fails,
当锁的持有者失败时，
so if lock holder fails,
如果锁持有者失败了，
basically zookeeper decides that lock holder has failed, correct,
zookeeper 确认锁持有者失败了，
as we just discussed,
正如我们刚才所讨论的，
then it is possible,
那是可能的，
that we're going to see some intermediate state.
我们会看到一些中间状态。
And remember like the whole rule that locks is,
记得锁的整个规则是，
like it's critical section,
它是临界区间，
you know you're some invariant is true,
一些不变量是 true ，
while you're going through the critical section,
当你通过临界区间的时候，
so that it might not be true,
所以这可能不是 true ，
but then at the end, you reestablish [invariant].
但到了最后，你会重建不变量。
In here, it's the case,
在这里，情况就是这样，
like it required lock,
它获取锁，
client requires lock, does some steps,
客户端获取锁，执行一些步骤，
and then you know maybe zookeeper decides
然后 zookeeper 决定，
if the client decides the client crash
如果客户端崩溃，
and basically revokes lock,
然后撤销锁，
but you know the state,
但是你知道状态，
you know the system might actually be some intermediate state,
系统可能在某种中间状态，
return invariant was not true, right,
返回不变量不是 true ，
so it's not the case,
所以不是这种情况，
that basically these logs guarantee adamicity of the critical section.
这些日志保证临界区间的[坚固性]。
So what, so what they do, what they useful for,
那么，它们做什么，它们有什么用处，
is for some other purposes,
是出于其他目的，
in fact sort of two primary use cases,
事实上，有两种主要用例，
one, I think is leader election,
一个，我认为是领导者选举，
so basically if we need a set of clients,
所以如果我们需要一组客户端，
that need to select the leader among them,
需要从它们当中选出领导者，
you know they can all try to basically create the lock file,
它们可以尝试创建锁文件，
one of them succeed,
其中一个成功了，
that's basically then becomes a leader,
成为领导者，
and that leader could clean up any intermediate states if possible if necessary,
如果有必要，领导者可以清理任何中间状态，
or you know do these atomic updates,
或者做这些原子更新，
using the ready trick,
使用 ready 的技巧，
where basically you do a bunch of writes to some file,
你对某个文件执行一些写入操作，
but then you expose the file only at the very end,
但只在最后[展示]文件，
and that way make a set of writes
通过这种方式进行一组写操作
actually are more transactional work.
是更具事务性的工作。
So that's one use case for these kind of locks,
所以，这是这类锁的一个使用案例，
the second use case is what I call soft locks,
第二个用例是我所说的软锁，
the soft locks you know the way to think about is that,
你可以考虑软锁是，
let's say we have a worker in the mapreduce style,
假设我们有一个 mapreduce 式的 worker ，
and the map,
而且 map ，
I want to basically arrange that you know every worker
我想安排每个 worker
executes a particular map task only once,
只执行一次特定的 map 任务，
and so the one way to do that,
所以，要做到这个的一种方法，
we basically take a lock out,
我们从外面获取一个锁，
you know for that particular input file,
对于特定的输入文件，
run you know the computation,
执行计算，
and then you know once the map is done,
然后，一旦 map 完成，
then you release the lock file,
然后释放锁文件，
so this will cost only one mapper to the common case to execute a particular task,
所以，通常情况下，执行特定任务只需花费一个 mapper ，
and and that's exactly what we want,
而这正是我们想要的，
but of course you know if the mapper would fail,
当然，如果 mapper 失败，
then the lock will be release,
那么锁就会被释放，
and then we might execute it a second time,
然后我们可能会再执行一次，
because somebody else will try to acquire a lock,
因为其他人会试图获取锁，
and so in that case,
所以在这种情况下，
you know for the case of mapreduce, that's perfectly fine, right,
对于 mapreduce 的情况，这是非常好的，
the, it's okay if the task is executed twice,
这个任务执行两次也没关系，
if happens twice.
如果发生两次。
And in some ways what it really is,
在某些方面，它到底是什么，
it's more performance optimization,
更多的性能优化，
in the usual case, you wanted to,
在通常的情况下，你想要，
you wanted that actually is execute the only once,
你想要只执行一次，
but you know if there's a failure,
但是如果失败了，
it might be the case,
情况可能是这样的，
that you're executing a map job twice,
你执行了两次 map 作业，
then that thing, you know the mapreduce means
然后那个东西， mapreduce 意味着
you set up in such a way, that actually that's okay.
你以这种方式设置，是可以的。
And so in those cases,
所以，在这些情况下，
these sort of locks are really useful, too.
这种锁也很有用。
Any questions about this, about this perspective for locks,
关于这个，有什么问题吗，关于锁的这个观点，
you know the zookeeper locks are not exactly like the Go locks,
zookeeper 锁与 Go 锁不太一样，
and it's just an important thing to keep in mind.
这是一件需要记住的重要事情。
Oh.
噢。
Yeah, go ahead, Alexander.
好的，继续， Alexander 。
Yeah, I had a question,
是的，我有个问题，
you said that, one of the differences is that,
你说过，其中一个区别是，
in zlocks, the, if, if the, if the server holding the lock dies,
在 zlock 中，如果持有锁的服务器宕机，
then the lock can be revoked,
那么锁就可以被撤销，
but, does that still happen if you don't pass the,
但是，如果你不通过，是不是仍然会发生，
because there's that flag called EPHEMERAL.
因为有一个标志是 EPHEMERAL 。
EPHEMERAL, yeah, it only happens with the ephemeral file.
EPHEMERAL ，是的，只有 ephemeral 文件才会发生这种情况。
Right, so can we just like emulate the Go locks by not passing EPHEMERAL.
是的，所以我们能不能通过不传递 EPHEMERAL 来模拟 Go 锁。
Okay, good, what would happen then,
好的，接下来会发生什么，
you create basically a persistent file,
你创建了一个永久文件，
the client dies.
客户端宕机。
You said the lock?
你是说锁？
And so the lock will keep on existing and nobody will release it,
锁将继续存在，没有人会释放它，
and we have a deadlock,
我们会陷入死锁，
because the one person that could release it is dead or crashed,
因为唯一可以释放它的已经宕机，或者崩溃，
and in fact, this is why EPHEMERAL [] there.
这就是为什么会有 EPHEMERAL 。
Is, is it actually the only, the only person who could release it,
它真的是唯一可以释放它的吗，
because anyone can delete that file, right,
因为任何人都可以删除那个文件，
you have a background, like.
你有[后台]，比如。
That will break,
这将破坏，
you know maybe the other client is still running,
可能另一个客户端仍在运行，
and also still thinks it holds a lock.
并且仍然认为它持有锁。
Sure.
好的。
You get are getting sort of, basically you're,
你会得到，
this is consensus problem all over again, right.
这又是一个共识问题。
And you know we,
你知道我们，
so this is sort of a clean way to get most of it,
所以，这是一种获得大部分信息的简单的方式，
but not all of it,
但不是全部，
if you will,
如果你愿意的话，
and I think if you want to make things atomic,
我想如果你想让东西变的原子化，
across a number of a set of writes atomic,
让一组写入原子化，
so you basically use this trick of,
所以你使用这个技巧，
use this trick, basically the ready trick,
使用这个技巧， ready 技巧，
where you do a bunch of writes and expose them at the same time.
执行很多写入，但是[同时]展示它们。
Could you explain those soft locks again?
你能再解释一下那些软锁吗？
Okay, soft locks means that basically an operation can happen twice.
好的，软锁意味着一个操作可以发生两次。
And so in the common case,
在常见的情况下，
if there's no crashes,
如果没有崩溃，
you know it will happen once,
它只会发生一次，
you know because you know the client will take a lock out,
因为客户端用一个锁，
will do the operation release,
会进行释放操作，
and, but if there client failed, halfway through,
但是如果客户端在半路失败了，
for example, then the lock would be automatically released by zookeeper,
然后锁将由 zookeeper 自动释放，
and then maybe a second client will execute the same map task.
然后可能是第二个客户端执行相同的 map 任务。
So in the case of leader election,
所以在领导者选举的例子中，
what's the intermediate state could get exposed here,
在这里可以暴露的中间状态是什么，
it seems that first.
这似乎是第一个。
Okay, pure leader election there would be no intermediate state,
好的，纯粹的领导人选举不会有中间状态，
but typically the leader will create a configuration file, right,
但是通常领导者会创建配置文件，
as we saw in zookeeper,
像我们在 zookeeper 中看到的那样，
where you know using the ready trick.
使用 ready 技巧。
I see, and so you just write the whole file,
我明白了，所以你把整个文件都写好了，
and then convert it atomic, use rename.
然后原子地进行转换，使用重命名。
Yep.
是的。
Sorry, could you explain what the ready trick is, exactly?
抱歉，你能具体解释一下 ready 技巧是什么吗？
I was hoping not to, I think we talked about last time.
我希望不用，我想我们上次谈过了。
Sorry.
抱歉。
So so maybe we, you can hold that question,
所以也许你可以保持这个问题，
well I'm happy to do it at the end of the lecture again,
我很高兴在课程结束后再讲一次，
because otherwise I have little time to actually talk about chain replication.
否则，我很少有时间来谈论链式复制。
Any other [] questions?
还有其他问题吗？
Okay, let me set the states where chain replication a little bit,
好的，让我设置一下链式复制的状态，
and then we'll also come back to zookeeper in some sense,
有时也会回到 zookeeper ，
and basically turns out,
事实证明，
there's sort of two common approaches to build replicated state machines,
有两种常见的方法来构建复制状态机，
and we really haven't called out these two approaches,
我们还没有提出这两种方法，
and we've seen them,
我们见过它们，
but I really talked explicitly about them,
但我很明确地谈到了它们，
I want to do this, this time explicitly.
我想这次是明确的。
So.
所以。
Because there's some interesting observations to be made
因为有一些有趣的观察
approaches to building replicated state machines.
用来构建复制状态机的方法。
And the first one is the one we've basically seen the labs,
第一个是我们在实验中看到的那个，
which is you run all operations you know through raft,
也就是运行所有操作通过 Raft ，
Raft, zookeeper Raft or you know Paxos,
Raft zookeeper 或者 Paxos ，
whatever you know consensus you know the consensus algorithm you're using,
无论使用什么共识算法，
and so this is sort of like the key value store, right,
这有点像键值存储，
in lab 3, where you do put and get operation,
在实验 3 中，你执行 put get 操作，
you run all the put and get operation through Raft,
你通过 Raft 执行所有 put get 操作，
and you know the service basically update you know the key value store state
服务更新键值存储状态，
as the operations are coming in on the apply channel,
当操作进入 apply channel 时，
and you know and basically we have our replicated states,
我们有自己的复制状态，
so this is how lab 3 works.
这就是实验 3 的工作方式。
It turns out that style where basically Raft is used,
事实证明， Raft 使用的这种风格，
the also run all the operations is actually not that common,
运行所有操作的情况并不常见，
we'll see some other designs later in the semester to do that too,
我们将在本学期晚些时候看到一些其他设计来实现这一点，
like Spanner does it,
比如 Spanner 实现了，
but it's not actually completely the standard approach
但这并不完全是标准的方法，
or more common approach actually is to have a configuration server,
或者更常见的方法是有一个配置服务器，
like zookeeper service,
比如 zookeeper 服务，
and the configuration service itself internally might use Paxos Raft or or ZAB or whatever,
配置服务内部可能使用 Paxos Raft ZAB 或任何其他，
and really the configuration service really plays the role of the coordinator or the master,
配置服务扮演着 coordinator 或 master 的角色，
like the GFS master,
就像 GFS master ，
and in addition to basically having configuration service
配置服务除了
actually implemented using one of these Raft Paxos algorithms,
使用 Raft Paxos 算法实现，
you actually run primary backup replication.
你也可以运行主备复制。
And so we think about GFS,
所以考虑 GFS ，
you know we saw early in the semester,
我们在本学期早些时候看到的，
has that sort of structure,
有这种结构，
like in the GFS was a master,
就像在 GFS 中有一个 master ，
and that basically determines which set of servers hold particular chunk,
这决定了哪组服务器保存特定的块，
so basically determined the replica group for a chunk,
确定区块的复制组，
and then the replica chunk group basically executed the primary backup replication,
然后复制块组组执行主备复制，
one of the chunks was the primary
其中一块是主节点，
and the other ones were the backups,
另一个是备份，
and they basically had a protocol that they use for primary backup replication.
它们有一个用于主备复制的协议。
You can think about VM-FT in a similar style,
你可以考虑 VM-FT 使用类似的形式，
where configuration server is basically test-and-set server,
其中配置服务器是 test-and-set 服务器，
which basically recorded who was actually the primary,
它记录了谁是主节点，
and then the primary backup have a protocol,
然后主备有一个协议，
to basically send you know channel operation down to channel,
发送[通道操作]到通道，
and so the primary backup is roughly in sync
因此，主备大致同步，
and implement replicated state machine.
实现复制状态机。
And this approach tends to be serve a more common approach,
这种方法往往是一种更常见的方法，
although the approach number one also happens.
虽然第一种方法也会发生。
One one way to think about this,
一种思考这个问题的方法，
is that you know if the Raft states,
如果 Raft 状态，
like for example our key value server in lab 3 would be gigantic,
比如，我们在实验 3 的键值服务器将是巨大的，
you know have a huge amount of this state,
有大量的这种状态，
you know terabytes of key value server,
数 TB 的键值服务器，
would Raft be very good match for that kind of application,
对于这种应用， Raft 会是非常好的匹配吗，
or what is the risk,
或者风险是什么，
or the potential problem?
或者潜在的问题？
We flush the log very often,
我们经常刷新日志，
so maybe that could be problematic.
所以，这可能会带来问题。
Could be problematic,
可能会有问题，
what how what's the size of the checkpoint,
检查点的大小是多少，
if our key value server is really big.
如果我们的键值服务器非常大。
It's linear in the size of the key value server.
它与键值服务器的大小成正比。
Yeah, so that could also be gigantic,
是的，所以这也可能是巨大的，
so at any you know any time the checkpoint has to be sent,
所以在任何时候，检查点必须被发送，
you know it's going to be a big checkpoint.
这将是一个很大的检查点。
And so the Raft it's not really sort of set up,
所以 Raft 并不是设置好的，
you know so the primary is going to communicate,
主节点需要通信，
you know the new primary is going to communicate [] snapshots,
新的主节点将与快照通信，
you did in lab 2d,
你在实验 2d 中所做的，
you know to the the backups,
到备节点，
they're gonna be big.
它们会很大。
And so you often want to be a little bit more clever plan
所以你想要更聪明的方案，
to synchronize and re-synchronize new servers,
重新同步新服务器，
and so and one reason that,
所以，一个原因，
basically often these things are split into two different pieces,
这些东西通常被分成两个不同的部分，
where the configuration service that basically small in terms of state,
其中配置服务在状态方面很小，
and then you know primary backup plan actually may replicate huge amount of data.
然后，主备方案可能复制大量数据。
And so this is why, one reason you see sort of both approaches.
这就是为什么，你看到这两种方法的一个原因。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
I'll come back to that at the end of the lecture again,
我会在课程结束时再讲到这一点，
but it's important to keep this in mind.
但重要的是要记住这一点。
So what approach or what benefits does 1 give over 2?
那么，方案 1 比 2 有什么好处呢？
You don't have to have two of them, right,
你不需要有它们两个，
in one, you basically have Raft,
在 1 中，你有 Raft ，
you run the operations for [] and then does the configuration for you too,
你运行[]操作，然后也为你进行配置，
so everything is in a single, single component,
所以，所有的东西都在一个单一的组件中，
and here in number two, we have two components,
在 2 中，我们有两个组件，
you know we have a configuration service, that includes Raft,
我们有一个配置服务，包括 Raft ，
and we have a primary backup scheme.
而且我们有一个主备方案。
So maybe this will become more clear,
所以，这个可能会变得更加清楚，
as we talk about chain replication.
当我们讨论链式复制时。
Yeah.
嗯。
I had a really quick question,
我有一个非常简短的问题，
so I [] for two,
所以第二个，
I guess would like what the advantage being that you have like,
优势是什么，
if consensus reached through the leader
如果通过领导者达成共识，
and the leader never fails, right, like.
领导者永远不会失败，对吧。
Yeah, so the advantage of two is that,
是的，所以第二个的优势是，
as we see in second in chain replication is,
正如我们随后会在链式复制中看到的，
there's a separate process that takes care of the configuration part,
有一个单独的进程负责配置部分，
and you don't have to worry about in terms of your primary backup replication scheme.
你不必担心你的主备份复制方案。
And that just decides like GFS,
这就像 GFS 一样决定了，
that's sort of like the master,
比如 master ，
it just decides for a couple of here,
它决定这里的几个，
set up have the service to form this particular replica group,
设置服务形成特定复制组，
and backup primary backup protocol doesn't have to think about this.
而主备协议不用考虑这个。
Thanks.
谢谢。
And so this is a good introduction to chain replication,
这是对链式复制的一个很好的介绍，
because the chain replication is exactly
因为链式复制正是
that sort of a primary backup replication scheme for approach 2.
方法 2 的主备复制方案。
And that is to say that you know chain replication assumes,
就是说，链式复制假设，
there is a configuration service,
有一个配置服务，
and I think they called the master process in paper.
我想他们在论文中成为 master 。
Then chain replication themselves,
然后链式复制本身，
there's a couple of cool properties.
有几个很酷的属性。
One, read operations or as they call them query operations involve only one server,
一，读操作或者他们称为查询操作只涉及一个服务器，
namely the tail as we've seen in a second.
也就是我们随后会看到的 tail 。
Another nice property about chain replication that has a very simple recovery plan.
链式复制的另一个很好的特性是具有非常简单的恢复方案。
I'm going to talk about all of these in more detail in the second.
我随后将更详细地讨论这些。
And presumably something that you started,
很可能一些事情开始，
have you you appreciate given the fact
你理解这个事实，
how complicated can be in Raft.
在 Raft 上能有多复杂。
And it provides actually strong strong properties, namely linearizability,
而且它提供了很强的性质，即线性一致性，
if we put and get operations.
如果我们进行 put 和 get 操作。
And finally just a lot of people askes,
最后，很多人问到，
you know actually a reasonable influential design,
是一个合理的有影响力的设计，
and used by quite a number of systems,
并被很多系统使用，
so these are used in practice.
所以这些都是在实践中使用的。
This is going to talk about each of these components,
这将讨论这些组件中的每一个，
and we'll get more detail,
我们会得到更多细节，
and then we'll come back to this sort of approach one versus approach two.
然后我们将回到方法一对比方法二。
So in terms of an overview,
所以从总体上来说，
oops,
糟糕，
in terms of an overview,
一个概述，
new sort of [] of the land,
新的[]类型，
you know there is a massive process or a configuration service,
这里有一个大的进程或一个配置服务，
and then basically keep track
然后跟踪
you know which server you know belong to a particular chain.
哪台服务器属于特定的链。
So S1 S2 S3
所以 S1 S2 S3 ，
you know basically have a record of what the chain is,
有一个关于是什么链的记录，
who the head is and who the tail is,
谁是头，谁是尾，
and so that could be configuration service,
所以这可能是配置服务，
and here we do actually have our service,
在这里，我们有我们的服务，
you know S1 S2 S3,
S1 S2 S3 ，
and one of them is the head,
其中一个是头部，
typically the one with the smaller number,
通常是数字较小的那个，
and one is the tail.
一个是尾部。
And so we have a client,
所以我们有一个客户端，
the client may talk to the configuration server,
客户端可以访问配置服务器，
who are actually part of the chain,
它是链的一部分，
and then it sends a write request to the head,
然后它向头部发送写请求，
so this is a protocol in chain replication,
所以这是一种链式复制协议，
the write request always goes to the, the head,
写请求总是发送到头部，
and what the head does, the head basically pushes,
头部所做的，头部推送，
you know the head actually applies the operation on its state,
头部对它的状态进行操作，
and maybe it has a disk associated with it,
也许它有一个关联的磁盘，
whatever the key value service on it,
键值服务在上面，
and then it sends the update,
然后它发送更新，
you know there's all of the operation down the chain in FIFO order and reliably,
所有的操作在链上按照先进先出的顺序可靠地进行，
so S1 will send the update to S2,
所以， S1 发送更新给 S2 ，
S2 it has make its own disk,
S2 有自己的磁盘，
apply the operation or the state change to its state,
将操作或状态更改应用于它的状态，
once it actually applyed it,
一旦它应用了它，
you know it will forward it to the last node in the chain,
它会把它发送到链中的最后一个节点，
in this, because there are only three nodes in this particular chain,
因为在这个链中只有三个节点，
you could have chains are longer,
你可以有更长的链，
if you want more availability,
如果你想要更多的可用性，
and when the last node gets the message with state change,
当最后一个节点收到状态改变的消息，
it applies to its state,
它应用于它的状态，
and then this is the charge actually sending an acknowledgment back to the client,
然后这是向客户端发回确认的[时机]，
so it's the tail who sends the acknowledgement back.
所以是尾部发回确认信息。
And so one way to think about this is that,
所以，考虑这一问题的一种方式是，
when the tail or in this case S3 you know actually applies to state change,
当尾部或在这种情况下 S3 应用了状态变化，
that's sort of the commit point.
这就是提交点。
And the reason that this is the commit point
之所以这是提交点，
is because subsequent reads always come from the tail,
是因为后续读取总是从尾部获取，
so if anybody or any other client you know does a read operation,
所以，如果任何客户端执行读操作，
they always go to the tail,
它们总是到尾部，
and the tail basically responds immediately back to them.
尾部会立即对它们做出反应。
So read operations go to the tail,
所以读操作到尾部，
so here's client 1, here is client 2,
这是客户端 1 ，这是客户端 2 ，
client 2 does read operation,
客户端 2 进行读操作，
it goes to the tail,
它到达尾部，
the tail responds and that's it.
尾部做出响应，就是这样。
And so there's a couple things that I wanted to point out,
所以有几件事我想指出，
the one of the interesting points out is that,
其中一个有趣的问题是，
the read operations just involve one server, right,
读操作只涉及一台服务器，
like if you remember from lab 3,
如果记得实验 3 ，
or if you have any progress,
或者如果你有任何进展，
we've started to do lab 3,
我们已经开始实验 3 ，
read operations actually involved,
读操作涉及，
you know in our implementation, read operation go through the Raft log,
在我们的实现中，读取操作通过 Raft 日志，
and all that kind of stuff,
以及所有东西，
the paper discusses an optimization,
论文讨论了一个优化，
but the read operation always goes to the leader,
但读取操作始终由领导者执行，
and the leader first has to contact the majority of the servers,
而领导者首先必须联系大多数服务器，
before it can execute the operation local.
在执行操作之前。
So what you see here is that,
所以你在这里看到的是，
the read operation actually go through tail,
读操作通过尾部，
so that different server from write operations,
写操作从不同的服务器，
so the read and write workload is excellent spread at least over two servers,
所以，读写工作负载至少分布在两台服务器上，
for more read operation involves only one server,
对于更多读操作只设计一台服务器，
there's never, doesn't have to talk to any other server,
不需要与任何其他服务器交互，
it can just respond immediately,
它可以立即做出响应，
and we'll see a little bit later,
我们稍后会看到，
why this is actually important,
为什么这很重要，
or why this is actually,
或者为什么，
what further optimization this allows.
这允许什么更多的优化。
So the commit point is really
所以提交点是，
you know the point that the write actually happens at the tail end,
写入发生在尾部的点，
because at that point, the write operation is visible to readers
因为在那一点，写操作可以被读取者看见，
and not before any other points.
而不是在任何其他点之前。
And this also you know provides this linearizability,
这也提供了线性一致性，
so it's pretty easy to see that,
所以很容易看到，
in the case of no crashes,
在没有崩溃的情况下，
scheme guarantees linearizability,
这个方案保证了线性一致性，
because the writes are all applied in sum total order at the head,
因为写入都是按整体顺序在头部应用，
and when the tail receives you know that update,
当尾部收到更新时，
it's, it's the commit point,
这是提交点，
it wants to respond to the client and sent the request back.
它想要响应客户端并发回请求。
If you know that same client immediately does a read operation,
如果同一客户端立即执行读取操作，
it will go to the tail,
它会到尾部，
and it will observe the last change.
它将观察到最后一次变化。
So, certainly within a single client,
所以，在单个客户端中，
basically all operations are totally ordered,
所有的操作都是完全有序的，
it's pretty easy to see that in client,
在客户端上很容易看出，
if client 2 start to read operation after client 1 operation is finished,
如果在客户端 2 读操作开始在客户端 1 操作完成之后，
and when it finished, when the tail has responded,
当它完成时，当尾部做出响应时，
so any read operation that starts after a write operation
所以，任何开始在写操作之后的读操作，
will observe you know the last or the result of the most recent write,
将观察到最后一次或最近一次写入的结果，
and so it's pretty easy to get an intuition here,
所以这里很容易得到一个直觉，
that you know this is going to provide us with linearizability.
这将为我们提供线性一致性。
Okay?
好的?
So, what I like to do now is actually to take a quick breakout room section,
我现在想要开始一个快速分组会议室，
and I would like you to discuss the question,
我想让你们讨论一下这个问题，
that was was post in lecture,
在课程中贴出的，
you know what could go wrong
会出什么问题，
or like what breaking linearizability,
或者什么打破线性一致性，
if instead of having the tail responds to the client,
如果不是让尾部响应客户端，
have the head responded to the client immediately
让头部立即响应客户端，
after it is received you know the write request,
在收到写请求之后，
nd maybe those are good topics
也许这些都是很好的话题，
or to debate a little bit,
或者可以稍微辩论一下，
and if you want to go in any other direction
如果你想从任何角度
to talk about chain replication of course welcome,
谈论链式复制，当然欢迎，
maybe that's something to start with.
也许这是一个开始。
So let's take a five minute breakout room,
所以让我们来个五分钟的分组会议室，
and then we'll do this and think,
然后我们这样做并想想，
let me see,
让我看看，
Jose, are you going to do it?
Jose 你来做吗？
And yeah and okay.
好的。
You have to make you something, or.
你得给做点什么，或者。
I don't think it's necessary.
我不认为这是必要的。
I think it Zoom change,
我认为是 Zoom 变化，
so it should be possible there, too.
所以在那里也是可能的。
Zoom, yep, that's right.
Zoom ，是的，没错。
Yep, okay.
好的，好的。
Jose, we're coming back.
Jose ，我们回来了。
Yeah, whenever you.
好的，你什么时候。
I'm ready.
我准备好了。
Okay, I mean I think I can close to Zoom.
好的，我想我可以关闭到 Zoom 。
Alright, we're back.
好的，我们回来了。
Okay, so you know just quickly to summarize,
好的，所以简单概括一下，
why you know that would break the linearizability,
为什么这会打破线性一致性，
so protocol change, change that was propagating was to
协议更改传播到，
you know both keep propagating to S1 and S2 S3,
继续传播到 S1 S2 S3 ，
but you know as soon as S1 actually has done,
但是一旦 S1 完成了，
which propagation as it responds back to a client,
消息传播，返回给客户端，
and clearly this will break the linearizability,
显然，这将会打破线性一致性，
because, let's say the client 1 did write,
假设客户端 1 写入，
got the acknowledgement back you know from S1,
从 S1 得到确认，
S1 of course has the write also in progress S2 and S3,
当然写入会继续到 S2 S3 ，
but maybe before you know S2 actually context S3,
但也许在 S2 与 S3 相关之前，
the client actually sends a read operation you know to S3,
客户端向 S3 发送一个读操作，
and of course, now it will return a value from before the write is done,
当然，现在它将返回写入完成之前的值，
so the client doesn't even observe its own write,
客户端甚至不能观察到自己的写入，
and so clearly break linearizability,
所以很明显打破了线性一致性，
and so it's very important,
所以这非常重要，
that you know as I said earlier,
正如我前面所说的，
that's the tail actually sends the acknowledgement back to the client,
是尾部发送确认给客户端，
because really the once the tail has processed the write operation,
因为一旦尾部处理了写操作，
that is actually really what the commit point is.
那就是提交点。
Any questions about that?
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
Okay, so this was sort of normal operations,
好的，所以这是正常的操作，
and let me talk a little bit about crashes,
让我来谈谈崩溃，
since it's 6.824 distributed systems,
因为它是 6.824 分布式系统，
so all the actually is where when the failures happen.
所以所有都是当失败发生时。
And one of the things that is cool about chain replication is,
链式复制最酷的一点是，
you know the number of failure scenarios is actually quite limited.
失败场景的数量是相当有限的。
And so, let me, basically three cases,
所以，让我来看三种情况，
namely the head fails, the one of the intermediate server fails, or tail fails.
头部故障，中间服务器之一故障或尾部故障。
So let's look at one of each one of each of those cases,
所以让我们来看看这些情况中的每一个，
so here's are you know the case we have a head S1,
这是一种情况，头部是 S1 ，
let's say that it applied U1, U2 and U3 sort three updates,
假设它应用了 U1 U2 U3 三个更新，
talks to S2,
与 S2 交互，
maybe S2 has done U2 and U1,
也许 S2 完成了 U2 和 U1 ，
and you know here we have S3 which is the tail,
这里我们有 S3 ，也就是尾部，
and it only has done U1 so far,
到目前为止，它只完成了 U1 ，
and so the client client was talking to S1,
所以，对于正在访问 S1 的客户端，
and we now want to think about what happens,
我们现在考虑会发生什么，
and what needs to happen in one of these crashes.
以及在其中一次崩溃中需要发生什么。
So let's start with the case that the head crashes,
所以让我们从头部崩溃的情况开始，
and so the head crashes, what needs to be done,
所以头部崩溃时，需要做什么，
this is an easy case or hard case?
这是一件容易的事还是一件难事？
Easier.
简单的。
I hope in easy case, why?
我希望是简单的情况，为什么？
You can just cut off the head,
你可以删除头部，
oh, sorry, the yeah, the head,
哦，抱歉，是的，头部，
and you know make S2 the head now.
现在让 S2 成为头部。
Yeah, you know, so what's going to happen correct is,
是的，所以会发生的事情是，
the configuration service discovers that S1 is gone,
配置服务发现 S1 不见了，
when decides if S1 is gone,
当确定 S1 不见了，
and then basically can promote S2 to be the head in the subsequent operations,
然后可以在后续操作中提升 S2 为头部，
and clients now in the future and talk to this guy,
未来的客户端访问这个节点，
and why is this correct,
为什么这是正确的,
so what operation have we lost?
那么我们丢掉了什么操作？
We lost U3.
我们失去了 U3 。
Yeah, is that a problem?
是的，这有什么问题吗？
That's valid to lose operations.
丢失操作是合法的。
Yeah, yeah, it's fair game to lose U3,
是的，丢失 U3 是合理的，
U3 has not been committed,
U3 尚未提交，
because only operations at the tail committed,
因为只有尾部的操作才会提交，
and so just as if the operation never happens,
所以，就像操作从未发生，
you know the client could not even have observed,
客户端甚至不会注意到，
you know that actually U this U2 or U3 actually it happens,
这个 U2 或 U3 发生了，
or U3 it should happen.
或者 U3 应该发生。
Okay?
好的？
So it's perfectly fine to do this,
所以这么做完全没问题，
why is it important configuration service actually involved here,
为什么配置服务涉及这里是重要的，
could like S2 decide on its own to become the head,
S2 可以自己决定成为领导者吗，
let's say yes, U2 talk to anyone anymore,
我们假设可以， U2 告诉任何节点，
and decides like whatever I want to become head,
决定无论如何，我要成为头部，
would that be valid?
这是合法的吗？
What is that, like maybe create a split.
那就像是创造分裂。
Yeah, yeah, that would create a split-brain, right,
是的，那会造成脑裂，
because it might, S2 might just be partitioned from S1,
因为 S2 可能与 S1 分区，
and so now both are heads,
所以现在两个都是头部，
maybe both are processing commands,
也许两者都在处理命令，
will be you know violate are,
将会是违规行为，
you know basically the sort of the whole [] having the total order,
全部[]都有整体顺序，
we can now.
我们现在可以。
Also, does S2 even know that S1 is a head,
同时， S2 知道 S1 是头部吗，
because it just receives.
因为它只是接受。
You probably got it from the configuration information in previous time,
你可能是从以前的配置信息中得到，
like when configuration service decides a new configuration,
比如当配置服务决定新配置时，
they can tell all the servers
它们可以告诉所有的服务器
and whatever and the clients actually care,
和任何关心的客户端，
you know here's the new configuration.
这是新的配置。
Does this only happen when S1 to S2 connection is separate
这是否仅在 S1 到 S2 连接断开时发生，
or wait what, what causes the split-brain again?
或者是什么导致了脑裂？
Split-brain would happen,
脑裂发生在，
if S2 on its own decided that S1 has failed and became the head,
如果 S2 自己决定 S1 失败并成为头部，
so we're not allowed to have that happen,
所以我们不允许这样的事情发生，
and the way actually the work out in practice is that,
在实践中，实现的方法是，
there is a configuration server,
这里有一个配置服务器，
that actually decides what is actually the current configuration,
它决定了当前的配置是什么，
and so if it decides that S1 is dead,
如果它确定 S1 已经宕机，
then it can inform S2 S3,
然后它可以通知 S2 S3 ，
saying like hey you guys are now the new chain and S2 the head,
说你们现在是新的链了， S2 是头部，
and when that change happens,
当这种变化发生时，
so in this case, basically S1 is dropped,
所以在这种情况下，会丢弃 S1 ，
nothing else has to happen,
不会有其他事情发生，
because S2 has,
因为 S2 有，
the only update that we lost,
我们丢失的唯一更新，
the one actually was not committed anyway,
并没有进行提交，
so there's nothing to be repaired further.
所以没有什么需要进一步修复的。
So making this go from this setting from three replica
所以从这个三个复制的设置开始，
with the dropping the head is basically pretty straightforward operation.
丢弃头部是相当简单的操作。
Okay?
好的?
Professor, I have a question,
教授，我有一个问题，
so there's there's an assumption here,
所以这里有一个假设，
that like the commands that,
就像命令一样，
like like leave S1 like will arrive in order at S2,
离开 S1 将按顺序到达 S2 ，
is that like, is that a reasonable assumption, for like.
这是不是一个合理的假设，比如。
Well, I think the way they,
好的，我认为它们的方式，
so they basically say,
所以他们说，
we need a reliable FIFO between S1 and S2, right,
我们需要在 S1 和 S2 之间一个可靠地先入先出，
S2 to S3,
以及 S2 到 S3 ，
and I think the way they implement, that is probably using TCP connection.
我想他们实现的方式很可能是使用 TCP 连接。
Okay, thanks.
好的，谢谢。
Okay, so let's look at the second case.
好的，让我们来看第二种情况。
So we're have you know S1, you know S2, S3,
所以我们有 S1 S2 S3 ，
and of course there could be more you know servers into chain,
当然，链中可能会有更多的服务器，
but like you know three enough for us to consider all the cases,
但是三个足够我们考虑所有的情况，
and so now what we want to do take the case, where a middle one crashes,
所以现在我们想要做的是，中间的一个崩溃了，
this one crashes.
这个崩溃了。
And so the configuration service at some point decides S2 crash,
所以，配置服务在某一时刻决定 S2 崩溃，
you know informs S1 S3, that basically they form the new chain,
通知 S1 S3 ，它们形成新的链，
and we're wondering about like what else needs to happen?
我们想知道，还有什么事情需要发生？
We saw in the first case,
我们在第一种情况中看到，
the head drops, then nothing really has to be done,
丢弃头部，就没什么好做的了，
other than updating the chain,
除了更新链之外，
now we're updating the chain,
现在我们更新链，
the question is, is anything needs to happen?
问题是，有什么事情需要发生？
The S1 needs to send to S3,
S1 需要发送给 S3 ，
the request that it sent to S2,
发送给 S2 的请求，
but didn't make it to S3.
但没发给 S3 。
Yes, we have you know U1 U2 U3,
是的，我们有 U1 U2 U3 ，
this guy had see U1 and U2,
这个看到 U1 和 U2 ，
and this guy see U1,
这个看到 U1 ，
and the U2 that's actually in progress,
U2 正在进行，
you know the I got lost S2,
我丢失了 S2 ，
basically S1 has to bring S3 up to date,
S1 必须使 S3 保持最新，
basically forward U2 and U3.
向前推进 U2 和 U3 。
Okay, so that's a little bit of work involved,
好的，这需要做一些工作，
let's consider the final case, the tail.
让我们来考虑最后一种情况，尾部。
So here we go again,
所以我们又来了，
we have three cases,
我们有三种情况，
S1, three servers S2, the third one S3.
三个服务器 S1 S2 S3 。
And, let's see, so the tail crashes.
让我们看看，尾部崩溃了。
And so at some point in time,
所以，在某个时间点，
the configuration service notices decides that the new chain is going to be S1 and S2,
配置服务通知决定新的链将是 S1 和 S2 ，
tells S1 and S2 that they are part of the new chain,
告诉 S1 和 S2 它们是新链的一部分，
and what else needs to happen?
还有其他需要发生的事情吗？
Well, let's write down,
好的，让我们写下来，
we know, this guy have seen U1 U2 and U3,
我们知道，这个看到 U1 U2 U3 ，
this guy have seen U1 U2,
这个看过 U1 U2 ，
so who becomes the new tail in this scenario?
那么，在这种情况下，谁将成为新的尾部？
S2.
S2 。
Yes, S2 becomes new tail,
是的， S2 成为新的尾部，
and anything else that needs to happen?
还有其他需要发生的事情吗？
I guess the client needs to be informed that S2 is the.
我想客户端需要被告知 S2 是。
Yeah, that's the client might learn from the configuration service, correct.
是的，客户端可以从配置服务获取。
And so yeah, but nothing else has to happen, right,
所以是的，但没有其他事情要发生，
because the, all the committed,
因为，所有提交的，
you know the no committed operations are lost,
没有提交的操作会丢失，
and you know, and as we are still in
由于我们仍然，
needs to still be actually propagated to S2 will be just happening.
仍然需要传播到 S2 会发生。
Okay, so dropping the tail is also reasonable straightforward.
好的，所以丢弃尾部也是直截了当的。
So dropping the tail, the head is a reasonable straightforward,
所以丢弃尾部，头部是很直截了当的，
dropping the middle one is a bit more complicated,
丢弃中间那个更复杂一些，
but not much more complicated.
但并不是很复杂。
And the key thing go I want to sort of emphasize here is,
我在这里想强调的关键是，
how does this compare to figure 7 and 8 in the Raft paper?
这与 Raft 论文上的图 7 和图 8 相比如何？
Maybe to.
也许是为了。
Yeah, go ahead.
好的，继续。
Question, so,
问题，所以，
that these new operations have been automatically.
这些新的操作都是自动的。
Um, sorry, I didn't hear you,
抱歉，我没有听到你说的话，
you were pretty pretty noisy connection there.
你那里的连接相当嘈杂。
Yeah, like I'm just saying, that S2 becomes new tail,
好的，我刚才说， S2 变成了新的尾部，
don't have to send acknowledgment back to the client,
不必向客户端发回确认吗，
and there are some entries that have been automatically committed.
还有一些条目是自动提交的。
Yeah, that might be the case,
是的，可能是这样的，
that what happens is the client is probably going to retry, right,
客户端可能发生的事情是重试，
and we have to have a separate duplication scheme like in lab 3 anyway,
我们必须有一个像实验 3 中的独立的重复检测方案，
and so there's kind of a couple different ways about how to do it,
有几种不同的方法可以做到这一点，
the paper are not particularly clear which one it will take.
论文并没有说明它使用哪一个。
Okay, I see, thank you.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
Yeah, like in that in that case,
是的，就像这种情况，
didn't the paper just say like,
论文不是说了，
you know it might like,
它可能会，
even if it doesn't respond it,
即使它没有回应，
could or could not have succeeded.
可能成功，也可能不成功。
Okay, so back to my actual original question,
好的，回到我原来的问题，
which is like, you know how does this contrast,
这个对比如何，
this picture of my my drawn picture here on this white board,
我在这个白板上画的图，
how does that contrast to figure 7 and 8?
对比图 7 和图 8 ，有什么不同？
Simpler.
更简单。
Yeah, I mean that's the key point I wanted to get across, right,
是的，这就是我想要表达的重点，
you know there's not that many cases to consider here,
这里要考虑的情况并不多，
basically three cases,
只有三种情况，
which is like slightly you know quite a bit simpler than the case of the Raft paper,
比 Raft 论文的情况要简单得多，
where the many to consider, the scenarios are quite complicated,
要考虑的情况很多，场景很复杂，
now part of that is because you know it's a chain, right,
部分原因是这是一条链，
you know things are pushed down in a very sort of straightforward manner,
事情以一种非常直截了当的方式推下来，
down the replication chain,
向复制链的下方，
and part of that is, of course,
当然，部分原因是，
the configuration part is sort of outsource to configuration manager manager.
配置部分外包给配置管理器。
But for the primary backup part of the recovery plan,
但是对于主备部分的恢复方案，
that's a reasonable straightforward,
这是直截了当的，
there are only three configurations to consider.
只有三种配置需要考虑。
One more point I want to make,
我还想提出一个点，
which is like how to add a replica,
就是如何添加复制，
because any system you know that here going to run for real time,
因为这里的任何系统都会实时运行，
really at some point you gotta add a new one in,
在某些时候，你需要添加一个新的，
because otherwise you're gonna lose,
因为否则你会丢失，
you start the three,
你开始有三个，
then you have two, then get one and then you have zero,
然后你有两个，然后有一个，然后就没有了，
and then you're on the [].
然后你就[]。
So, you know you have to add new replica,
所以，你必须添加新的复制，
so let's to consider the case,
所以让我们来考虑一下这个情况，
so here's S1, it is the head,
这是 S1 ，它是头部，
let's say we're in a scenario,
假设我们在一种情景中，
where you know we have S1 and S2 who's the tail,
我们有 S1 S2 ， S2 是尾部，
and basically we want to bring up S3,
我们想要添加 S3 ，
and it turns out you know as the paper described,
事实证明，正如论文所描述的那样，
it was most convenient to actually do this at the tail end of it,
在它的尾部做这件事是最方便的，
so basically make the new server, the new tail.
所以创建新的服务器，新的尾部。
And so the way that we proceed is,
所以，我们继续进行的方式是，
like the client is here,
比如客户端在这里，
talking to S2,
访问 S2 ，
because that's the current tail,
因为这是当前的尾部，
S3 comes up,
S3 出现，
and basically the first thing it does is,
它做的第一件事是
it actually copies you know old state from S3 to,
将 S3 中的旧状态复制到，
from S2 to S3.
从 S2 到 S3 。
And so this may take hours, right,
所以这可能需要几个小时，
where you know tens of minutes or maybe indeed multiple hours,
几十分钟，甚至几个小时，
you're going to copying gigabytes of data or terabytes of data from S2 to S3,
你将从 S2 向 S3 复制数 GB 或数 TB 的数据，
but while that's happening,
但当这一切发生的时候，
you know S2 and S3 can just serve request,
S2 S3 能服务于请求，
of course it does have to remember which ones are came in after S3 start copy,
当然，它必须记住哪些是在 S3 开始复制之后进入的，
so keep a list of all the updates that are sort of happened,
所以保持一份所有发生更新的列表，
but there have not been propagated to S3 yet,
但还没有传播到 S3 ，
at some point S3 done with all the copying,
在某个时刻， S3 完成了所有复制，
and basically tells S2,
告诉 S2 ，
okay, man, I'm ready you know to become the tail,
好的，伙计，我准备好了，成为尾部，
I got all the state,
我得到了所有状态，
S2, so sends an email, sends email, sends message to S2,
S2 ，发送邮件，发送消息给 S2 ，
saying, okay, I want to be the tail,
说，好的，我想成为尾部，
S2 responses, like yeah that's okay,
S2 回应，比如，是的，可以，
but once your applied all the updates.
但是一旦你应用了所有的更新。
And so basically S2 sends the updates in response to this,
所以， S2 发送更新响应这个，
I want to go on to come to a tail request,
我想继续一个尾部请求，
in response that to S3,
作为对 S3 响应，
S3 replies the updates,
S3 回复更新，
and then becomes you know the tail,
然后变成尾部，
and you know clients that we're talking to S2,
正在与 S2 交互的客户端，
and S2 can tell the client,
S2 可以告诉客户端，
you know from now on, I'm not tail anymore,
从现在开始，我不再是尾部了，
you should talk to S3,
你应该访问 S3 ，
and so they can swap you know that direction.
所以它们可以切换方向。
And so that's the way to add a replica into a chain.
所以，这就是将复制添加到链中的方法。
So question on this,
所以关于这个的问题，
don't you run into this like infinite loop problem,
你不会遇到这样的无限循环问题吗，
where S2 sends updates to S3,
S2 将更新发送到 S3 ，
and when S3 is like updating, its also serving more requests,
当 S3 更新时，它也服务于更多的请求，
so as more updates,
由于更多的更新，
that needs to send and goes back and forth?
它需要来回发送？
No, no, once S2 have sent the updates,
不，一旦 S2 发送了更新，
S3 have not seen yet, you know to S2 to S3,
S3 还没有见过，到 S3 ，
then from then on the normal chain replication,
然后从那时起，正常的链式复制，
whenever S2 gets a request,
每当 S2 收到请求时，
you know update from S1,
来自 S1 的更新，
it forwards it to S3.
它将它推给 S3 。
Right, but S3 can become the tail
是的，但是 S3 可以成为尾部
until it is successfully processed all the updates.
直到它成功处理了所有更新。
Oh, yeah so, yeah, once it sets up the TCP channel,
哦，是的，所以，一旦它建立了 TCP 通道，
basically S2 can just say like for,
S2 可以说，
once you've processed these guys,
一旦你处理完这些，
you can become the tail,
你可以成为尾部，
because you've seen everything.
因为你看过所有东西。
I mean.
我是说。
And everything else you can be pipelined after that, right,
后面的所有东西都可以按顺序排序，
in the same TCP channel.
在同一个 TCP 通道中。
It could become the tail, right, right after,
它可以变成尾部，
like even before it processes the update,
甚至在处理更新之前，
as long as it doesn't serve requests.
只要它不服务于请求。
As long as it doesn't serve requests exactly, right,
只要它不服务请求，是的，
it just has to process all the updates,
它只需要处理所有更新，
that S2 is received S3 not,
S2 收到的 S3 没有，
once we updated those,
一旦我们更新了这些，
then it becomes tail and start processing request.
然后它变成尾部，并开始处理请求。
I see, so blocks like requests for a moment,
我明白了，所以暂时阻塞请求，
while it processes new update.
当它处理新的更新时。
Okay?
好的?
Okay, so now I wanna come back you know to basically questions lots of people ask,
好的，现在我想回到很多人问的问题上，
how this contrast to sort of,
这个比较起来怎么样，
how are the CR properties, chain replication properties,
CR 属性，链式复制属性，
how do how does it compare,
它是如何比较的，
and one of the good, one of the good properties
其中一个好的属性，
and mostly with [respectful] in comparison to Raft.
大多数与 Raft 进行比较。
And of course I got to say,
当然，我得说，
of course like the chain replication just influence the primary backup scheme,
当然，链式复制只影响主备方案，
but not the configuration service,
而不是配置服务，
so we'll come back to that a little bit more in detail,
所以我们会更详细地谈到这一点，
but a couple things that we can know,
但有几件事我们可以知道，
we just compare sort of the way,
我们只比较方式，
the Raft protocol works with the chain replication protocol.
Raft 协议和链式复制协议的工作方式。
And first of all you know we can achieve,
首先，我们可以得到，
positive aspect you know chain replication is that
链式复制的积极方面是，
the client RPCs are you know split between to the head and the tail,
客户端的 RPC 拆分到头部和尾部，
that's a load of actually serving any client operation
为任何客户端操作提供服务的负载
that can be split actually between two of them,
可以在它们两个之间拆分，
they don't have to run through the leader as in in Raft.
它们不必像在 Raft 中那样通过领导者。
Furthermore, the head sends the update once,
此外，头部发送更新一次，
so unlike in Raft,
所以不同于 Raft ，
where the head or the leader basically sends updates,
头部或领导者发送更新，
the log entry to every peer,
（发送）日志条目到每个节点，
in this particular scheme,
在这个方案中，
actually it's only happened the head always sends one basically RPC,
头部总是只发送一个 RPC ，
and so there are fewer messages involved.
因此涉及的信息更少。
Reads or query operations involve only, only the tail,
读取操作只涉及尾部，
unlike in the Raft,
与 Raft 不同，
you know the if you, even if you implement the read-only optimization,
即使你实现了只读优化，
the read-only optimization avoid, having read operation go through the log
读操作通过日志，
and being appended to all the logs to peers,
并附加到所有节点的日志中，
but it still requires that the leader actually contact the majority of the peers
但这仍然需要领导者与大多数节点联系，
to decide when it's actually an operation can be served.
来决定它是不是可以服务的操作。
So another positive aspect of this [] is a simple crash recovery,
另一个[]的积极方面是简单的崩溃恢复，
as we talked about.
正如我们所说的。
But you know a major downside compared to sort of the Raft scheme
但是与 Raft 方案相比，它的一个主要缺点是，
is that you have one failure requires reconfiguration,
你有一个故障就需要重新配置，
and the reason now that the reconfiguration required is,
需要重新配置的原因是，
because like write actually have to go through the whole chain,
因为写入必须通过整个链，
and so, and the write cannot acknowledge
所以，写操作无法确认，
until that every server in the chain actually has processes.
直到链中的每台服务器都已经执行。
And that is actually slightly different, correct,
这略有不同，
in Raft, as you well know,
在 Raft 中，如你所知，
because assume it's basically majority the peers
因为假设大多数节点，
actually accepted the particular write operation, appended to their logs,
接收写操作，追加到它们的日志中，
the system can just proceed,
系统就可以继续运行，
and so there's actually no interruption at all,
所以根本没有中断，
if one server fails, for example,
如果一台服务器出现故障，
if the remaining servers still form a majority,
如果剩余的服务器仍然构成大多数，
while in chain replication,
而在链式复制中，
if one server would fail,
如果一台服务器发生故障，
then you know some reconfiguration actually has to happen,
一些重新配置必须发生，
which means there's gonna be a short period probably downtime, right.
这意味着可能会有一段很短的停机时间。
Does that make sense?
这能理解吗？
Now I want to make one more point
现在我想再提出一点，
sort of in contrast you know to sort of the Raft replication scheme is this,
相比 Raft 复制方案是这样的，
because the read operations involve only one server,
因为读取操作仅涉及一个服务器，
there's a cool extension,
有一个很酷的扩展，
if you will, that actually gets really high read performance,
如果你愿意，它会获得非常高的读取性能，
and so the basic idea is as follows,
所以基本思想是这样的，
the basic idea is basically to split,
基本的想法是拆分，
you know the split objects or they call volumes in the paper,
拆分对象或他们在论文中所说的 volume ，
split the objects across multiple chains.
将对象拆分到多个链中。
So instead of having one chain that I've done in the previous boards,
不是像我在以前的板上做的只有一个链，
we're going to have multiple chains.
我们将有多条链。
And so for example, we might have CH1 in chain 1,
比如我们可能有链 1 ， CH1 ，
S1 is the head, S2 is the middle guy and S3 is the tail.
S1 是头部， S2 是中间的， S3 是尾部。
And chain 2, you know we're going to rotate things around,
链 2 ，我们旋转物体，
S2 as the head, S3 is the middle guy,
S2 是头部 ， S3 是中间的，
oops, S3 is the middle guy and S1 is the tail.
糟糕， S3 是中间的， S1 是尾部。
And chain 3, we're going to arrange basically S3 as the head guy,
链 3 ，我们会安排 S3 作为头部，
S2 as, oops S1 the middle guy and S2 is the tail.
S2 是，糟糕， S1 是中间的， S2 是尾部。
Basically we're gonna do is,
我们要做的是，
we're going to split objects across these multiple chains,
我们将把对象分成多个链，
so the configuration service basically has a map,
所以配置服务有一个映射，
you know saying like you know shard 1,
比如分片 1 ，
you know objects in shard one go to chain 1,
在分片 1 中的对象到链 1 ，
object in shard 2 go to chain 2,
分片 2 中的对象到链 2 ，
objects in shard 3 you know go to chain 3.
分片 3 中的对象到链 3 。
And what is the cool part about it is that,
它最酷的地方是，
you know we have multiple tails,
我们有多个尾部,
and S1, S3 is tail for some chain,
S3 是某个链的尾部，
S1 is a tail for some chain,
S1 是某个链的尾部，
S2 is a tail for some chain,
S2 是某个链的尾部，
and basically read operations to different chain
到不同链的读操作
can now be completely executed in parallel,
现在可以完全并行执行，
so if the read operations hit all the different shards,
所以，如果读操作命中不同的分片，
sort of uniform spread,
均匀的分布，
basically you know our read throughput is going to increase linearly
我们的读吞吐量会线性增加
with the number of tails that we have,
随着我们拥有的尾部数量，
and in this case, we have three tails,
在这种情况下，我们有三个尾部，
so we get three times to read performance.
所以我们获得三倍的读性能。
So we did basically sort the same,
所以我们做了同样的事情，
so we get a little bit of the same properties the zookeeper had,
所以我们得到了一些 zookeeper 拥有的相同的属性，
where the read performance can be excellent,
读性能可以很好，
scale with the number of servers,
随着服务器数量的增加而扩展，
but we also get not only that,
但我们得到的不仅是这些，
we get the scale part,
我们得到了扩展部分，
and we maintain the linearizability,
并且我们保持了线性一致性，
in this scheme, we don't have to actually give up on linearizability.
在这个方案中，我们不必放弃线性一致性。
So we get to two nice properties,
所以我们得到两个好的性质，
namely good read performance and effective scaling with the number of servers,
良好的读取性能和随服务器数量的有效扩展，
at least for reads to different chains,
至少对于读取不同的链，
and we got actually and we maintain linearizability.
并且我们保持了线性一致性。
Any questions about this?
关于这个，有什么问题吗？
Sorry, in this case,
抱歉，在这种情况下，
the client when they are deciding which chain to read from,
客户端什么时候决定从哪个链进行读取，
would they be able to, to do like to decide themselves
它们能够自己决定吗，
or do they need to contact the configuration server to decide.
或者它们是否需要联系配置服务器来决定。
Yeah, so this is a great question,
是的，所以这是一个很好的问题，
so typically and the paper actually doesn't really explicit about it,
所以通常情况下，这篇论文并没有明确地说明这一点，
you know they talk about maybe talking through proxy to servers,
它们谈到也许可以通过代理访问服务器，
what you will do in lab 4 is
你在实验 4 中要做的是
basically you will download the configuration,
你会下载配置，
the configuration will include the shard assignment,
配置包含分片分配，
and you download that from the configuration server.
然后你从配置服务器下载。
You need to be careful about
你需要注意
how you order the servers in each of the chains,
如何对每个链中的服务器进行排序，
prevent like a particular chain from being oversaturated
防止某个链过饱和，
or particular [link] between like two servers.
或两个服务器之间的特定[链路]。
Yeah, this, this, this, this scheme doesn't really take that into account,
是的，这个方案没有考虑到这一点，
you can imagine like the configuration plan or the configuration manager
你可以想象配置方案或配置管理器
has a sophisticated model of actually how the network is laid out,
拥有网络布局的复杂模型，
and you know can be very careful about how the chains are done,
可以非常小心地注意链是如何做的，
maybe even shard more shards to one chain,
可能更多的分片在一条链上，
you know fewer shards to another chain,
而更少的分片在另一条链上，
all the stuff is in principle possible,
所有的事情原则上都是可能的，
because the configuration manage can just compute anything it likes,
因为配置管理可以计算任何东西，
and basically says here's the assignment.
并且说这是分配。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Can even rebalance, if it wants to.
如果它想的话，甚至可以重新平衡。
Answer the question,
回答问题，
could you explain again how linearizability is kept under this extension?
你能再解释一下线性一致性是如何在这个扩展下保持的吗？
Well, nothing has really changed,
好的，什么都没有真正改变，
we're still doing primary backup using a chain,
我们仍在使用链进行主备，
and and so you know we basically carry over the linearizability from the single chain
所以，我们从单链延续了线性一致性，
and that's it.
就是这样。
This might be like speculative,
这可能是猜测的，
but how this compared to,
但这个相比，
I guess maybe it's equivalent of just having groups of servers for each like link,
我想这可能相当于每个链接有一组服务器，
instead of having reusing the same ones,
而不是重复使用相同的那个，
or not for each link,
或者不是针对每个链接，
but for each step in the chain,
而是针对链中的每一步，
so like S1 is like three servers,
所以，就像 S1 有三台服务器，
S2 has three servers,
S2 有三台服务器，
instead of reusing the same one
而不是重复使用相同的那个，
and entering from different points.
从不同的角度进入。
Yeah yeah, what would be the advantage of that scheme that you imagine?
是的，你想象的那个方案有什么好处？
I mean just for scalability,
我的意思是，为了可扩展性，
while also maintain linearizability.
同时保持线性一致性。
Well, the the reason that this scheme is attractive is that,
好的，这个方案有吸引力的原因是，
because we have the tail might have quite a bit of load,
因为我们尾部可能有相当多的负载，
but the middle guy doesn't,
但中间的那个不会，
and you know by having sort of this arrangement,
通过这样的安排，
we spread the load across all servers.
我们将负载分散到所有服务器上。
I see, okay.
我明白了，好的。
Okay, good.
好的，很好。
So maybe I want to summarize here,
所以也许我在这里总结一下，
and sort of talk a little bit about,
然后稍微讨论一下，
so we saw the approach 1,
所以我们看到了方法 1 ，
which we're do in lab, which we do in lab 3,
我们在实验 3 所做的，
which is run all the operations through Raft,
运行所有的操作通过 Raft ，
and or the replication, you know the configuration and replication is all built using Raft
或者配置和复制都是使用 Raft 构建的，
and nothing else is involved,
而且没有牵涉其他东西，
and then sort of this approach 2,
然后是方法 2 ，
you know which is the topic of this particular paper,
是这篇论文的主题，
where there's a configuration server,
有一个配置服务器，
perhaps built using Raft or Paxos anyone
可能使用 Raft 或 Paxos 或其他，
and a primary backup replication scheme,
以及一个主备复制方案，
and primary backup using chain replication.
同时主备使用链式复制。
And you can see,
你可以看到，
you know hopefully there's a little clear,
希望这里更清楚，
there's some attractive properties to approach 2,
方法 2 有一些吸引人的性质，
in the sense that,
从某种意义上说，
you can get scalable read performance,
你可以获得可扩展的读取性能，
on the primary backups,
在主备上，
of course not on the configuration server,
当然不在配置服务器上，
because it runs Raft,
因为它运行 Raft ，
like you know you're doing approach 1,
你在使用方法 1 ，
but you can at least you know,
但你至少可以，
maybe scale read performance for actual operations on the replicas
可能对复制上的操作扩展读性能，
or on the primary backup scheme,
或者在主备方案中，
put and get operations.
put 和 get 操作。
The other thing that is nice about this is that,
这个的另一个好处是，
the if you have data is very very large,
如果数据非常大，
you know you can have more specialized synchronization
你可以有更专业的同步，
or scheme to basically copy the state from one machine to another machine.
或者将状态从一台机器复制到另一台机器的方案。
And you know the chain replication or when any sort of primary backup schemes,
链式复制或任何类型的主备方案，
sort of separated from the configuration server,
与配置服务器分开，
allows you to do that easily.
使你可以轻松地做到这一点。
And so it's quite common,
所示，这是很常见的，
that you know the practice you know people for approach 2,
人们在实践中使用方法 2 ，
although it is also not impossible
尽管也不是不可能，
to actually use approach 1 for your replicated state machine,
对复制状态机使用方法 1 ，
including serving operations like put get operations,
包括像 put get 操作这样的服务操作，
and in fact, the lab 3 would do it,
实际上，实验 3 会这样做，
we will see later paper in this semester Spanner,
我们将在本学期晚些时候看到论文 Spanner ，
and that actually uses Paxos to actually also do the operations.
它也使用 Paxos 来完成操作。
Any further questions here?
这里还有什么问题吗？
If not,
如果没有，
then I wish you all good luck on the mid-term on Thursday,
那么我祝大家在周四的期中考试中好运，
and I'll see you in person, well, virtually in person next week.
我会在下周当面见你，虚拟的当面。
And if you have any questions,
如果你有任何问题，
please feel free to hang around,
请随意留在这里，
and I'll do my best to answer them.
我会尽最大的努力回答他们。
I have a question about something that you mentioned about Raft,
我有一个关于你提到的关于 Raft 的问题，
so you mentioned that all the reads have to go through the majority of servers,
你提到，所有的读取都必须通过大多数服务器，
but I'm not quite sure I understand why,
但我不太明白为什么，
because the leader has all of the committed entries, right.
因为领导者有所有提交的条目，对吧。
Yeah, there's two two schemes,
是的，有两个方案，
if the leader,
如果领导者，
so either you run into a situation,
所以要么你遇到这样一种情况，
where all recent writes are served by the leader, right,
所有最近的写入都由领导者提供服务，
or you know there's a possibility to serve from principle
或者从原则上讲，
and read operation from another peer,
读操作由其他节点提供服务，
but then you have to contact first majority of the servers
然后你必须首先联系大多数服务器，
to make actually majority that you have the last operation.
以确保大多数有最近的操作。
Got it,
明白了,
so that that requirement is,
所以，这个需求是，
if we want to spread all the reads across every peer.
如果我们想要将所有读取分布在每个节点上。
We have to be more sophisticated
我们必须更老练一些，
and we cannot do it on our own,
我们不能靠自己做到这一点，
because that would definitely break linearizability.
因为这肯定会破坏线性一致性。
Right, but if everything goes to the leader.
是的，但如果一切都通过领导者。
Then when you're going there, correct,
然后当你到达那里的时候，
except you have to do this trick,
你必须使用这个技巧，
where you ask for an empty agreement,
你要求一个空的[同意]，
at the beginning of every new term,
在每个新 term 开始的时候，
just to make sure that you actually are up to date.
只是为了确保你确实是最新的。
Okay, thank you.
好的，谢谢。
Could you, quickly go over again,
你能不能，再快速地说一下，
when you're adding a new server at the tail,
当你在尾部添加新服务器时，
so just to make sure I understand,
所以为了确保我明白，
so essentially it starts this process
所以，实质上，它启动了这个过程，
for copying all the data from S2 to S3
将所有数据从 S2 复制到 S3 ，
and then if it receives requests for any of that data,
然后，如果它接收到对任何数据的请求，
while that is still happening,
在这种情况仍在发生的时候，
then S3 is going to ask S2 for anything that it still has directly,
然后， S3 将直接向 S2 索要其仍有的任何东西，
and it's going to get it and then respond.
它会得到，然后做出响应。
Yep.
是的。
And then it keeps doing that,
然后它继续这样做，
until it gets data that S2 no longer has,
直到它获得 S2 不再有的数据，
and then it just goes live essentially.
然后它就直接上线了。
Yeah, or you could do slightly differently,
是的，或者你可以稍微改变一下，
you know you could actually have S3 could basically tell S2,
你可以让 S3 告诉 S2 ，
S3 can become the leader, oh, sorry, the tail,
S3 可以成为领导者，抱歉，尾部，
and basically don't process any common operations from the client yet,
不要处理来自客户端的任何操作，
until it actually has has received the remaining operations from S2.
直到它收到来自 S2 的剩余操作。
Oh, so in that case, S2 is still the tail.
哦，那么在这种情况下， S2 仍然是尾部。
Yeah.
是的。
Until S3 gets everything.
直到 S3 得到一切。
Basically, the paper describes one particular way of doing it,
基本上，这篇论文描述了一种特殊的方法，
you know there's a couple ways of doing it.
有几种方法可以做到这一点。
But if you do that then,
但如果你这么做了，
like how long do you wait to get everything,
那么你要等多久才能获得所有东西，
I think I also had the same confusion as someone else.
我想我也有和其他人一样的困惑。
You know, you know in what order the switch is happening, correct,
你知道转换发生的顺序，
so for example like S3, so S2 let's say maybe has a big operations through hundreds,
举个例子，假设 S2 有 100 的运算，
you start to copy operations,
你开始复制操作，
like with snapshots with a Raft,
就像 Raft 中的快照，
so when the copy operation is done,
所以，当复制操作完成时，
S3 is up to data until hundred, right,
S3 更新到 100 ，
then you know maybe S2 already has 10 more operations,
然后也许 S2 已经多了 10 个操作，
so it has 101 102 and 103, right,
所以它有 101 102 和 103 ，
and basically S3 can you know contact S2,
S3 可以联系 S2 ，
say give me your remaining operations,
说，把你剩余的操作给我，
and S2 says, like well remaining operations 101 to 110,
S2 说，好的，剩余的操作是 101 到 110 ，
and as a side effect,
作为连带的效果，
you know S3 also tells S2 like stop being the tail,
S3 也告诉 S2 不要再做尾部了，
and S2 response with those operations,
S2 使用这些操作做出响应，
S3 applies there operation 101 to 110,
S3 应用这些操作从 101 到 110 ，
and then tells client it means it is tail,
然后告诉客户端它是尾部，
but it doesn't process any commands from clients yet
但它还不能处理来自客户端的任何命令，
or read operation from client yet,
或来自客户端的读操作，
until it actually process 101 to 110.
直到它处理了 101 到 110 。
Okay, okay, I see, I see, okay, understand.
好的，好的，我明白了，理解了。
I have another question,
我还有一个问题，
oh sorry.
哦，抱歉。
No, go ahead, go ahead.
不，继续，继续。
Okay, my question was a little similar to the extension that he talked about,
好的，我的问题和他说到的扩展有些类似，
I thought, I thought about,
我在想，
could you could you do a tree instead of a chain, so.
你能不能使用一个树而不是一个链，所以。
I think there's the,
我认为有，
there's other data structures possible,
还有其他可能的数据结构，
like for example, you know number of people in email proposed,
例如，很多人在电子邮件中建议，
that you could have S1,
你可以有 S1 ，
then you could have like S3 4 5, all the intermediate ones,
然后你可以有 S3 4 5 ，所有都是中间的，
you know S1 talks to them in parallel to all the intermediate ones
S1 与所有中间的并行交互，
and the intermediate ones talk all to the tail,
中间的与尾部交互，
is that what you mean with a tree?
你说的树是这个意思吗？
I meant more if there would be,
我的意思是更多，
like a number of leaves,
比如很多叶子节点，
there would be at all roughly the same height,
它们的高度大致相同，
so like a balanced tree,
就像一棵平衡树，
and then the leaves will have like a chain going through them,
然后叶子会有一条链穿过它们，
and I think the linearizability can be broken here,
我认为线性一致性在这里可以被打破，
if you like, oh, if you'd think harder about it,
如果你仔细考虑一下，
but it would have the nice property,
但它将拥有好的性质，
that you wouldn't,
你不需要，
like the the propagation can delay would be like [logarithmic]
现在的传播延迟可以是[对数式的]，
instead of linear as here,
而不是这里的线性的，
and you could read from all the leaves.
你可以从所有的叶子节点读取。
Yeah, okay, reading from all the leaves is dangerous, right,
好的，从所有的叶子节点读取是危险的，
because they might have,
因为它们可能有，
you know one client might have talked to another leaf earlier
一个客户端可能早些时候访问过另一个叶子节点，
and leaves might not be in sync,
叶子节点可能不同步，
so that sounds dangerous to me,
所以我觉得这听起来有危险，
maybe your your scheme is a little bit more sophisticated than I'm thinking,
也许你的方案比我想象的更复杂，
the depth of the tree or the depth of the chain
树的深度或者链条的深度
really govern by the meantime between failure, right,
是由失败之间的时间决定的，
if you're on the,
如果你在，
if you typically run with 3 servers, 3 to 5 servers,
如果你通常运行 3 台服务器， 3 到 5 台服务器，
because that's good enough for your high availability,
因为这对你的高可用性来说已经足够好了，
then because you can recover from 4 servers,
然后，因为你可以从 4 台服务器恢复，
before the whole thing is done,
在整件事完成之前，
then that really covers the depth of the chain,
然后这就覆盖了链的深度，
and yeah we'll introduce some latency.
是的，我们会引入一些延迟。
Okay, that make sence, thank you.
好的，有道理，谢谢。
Chain will generally be short.
链一般都是短的。
You're welcome.
不用谢。
Is this the only case where the entire chain would go down,
这是唯一整个链宕机的情况吗，
if all the servers in the chain went down?
如果链中的所有服务器都宕机了？
Yeah.
是的。
Thank you.
谢谢。
I also was curious how you know maintain the strong consistency,
我也很好奇如何保持强一致性，
when like S1 S2 and S3 can all do the read in this slide.
在这个幻灯片中， S1 S2 S3 都可以进行读取。
You get strong consistency per per shard or per object,
你可以获得每个分片或每个对象的强一致性，
you know that's assigned to the chain, right.
这是分配给链的，对吧。
So if here read, you write one object,
所以如果写入一个对象，
you write object one, you read object one,
你写入对象一，你读取对象一，
all those operations are going to go through the same chain,
所有这些操作都经过相同的链，
and so you get strong consistency for that particular object.
所以，对于那个特定的对象，你会得到强一致性。
Oh, got it.
哦，知道了。
But it may not be the case,
但情况可能并非如此，
across all the objects, we have strong consistency.
在所有的对象上，我们都有强一致性。
No, I don't, I will, let me hesitate that.
不，我不，让我犹豫一下。
Let me hesitate,
让我犹豫一下，
I think you know that requires maybe more machinery.
我想这可能需要更多的机制。
Well, what does that mean,
那么，这是什么意思，
like across all the objects getting strong consistency.
所有的对象获得强一致性。
I think, the you read write object one,
我认为你读写对象一，
you read or write object two,
你读或写对象二，
and then some client read object one,
然后一些客户端读取对象一，
are you going to yet,
你会获得，
basically you know if you have a client to read both objects,
基本上，如果你有一个客户端读取这两个对象，
are you are guaranteed to see total order and linearizability.
你能不能保证看到整体顺序和线性一致性。
Is that like serializability?
这类似于可串行化吗？
Serializability slightly different,
可串行化略有不同，
you know maybe, let's not talk about serializability,
也许，我们不要讨论可串行化，
we'll come back, we'll get that later in a couple weeks.
我们会回来，我们会在几周后讨论。
Yeah, and.
嗯。
I [] to actually make a commitment right now,
我现在[]做出承诺，
I need to think a little bit about it.
我需要考虑一下。
Okay, that's totally fair.
好的，这完全可以。
So the question is like,
所以问题是这样的，
you know you have consistency or linearizability for a single client reading and writing,
你具有单个客户端读取和写入的一致性或线性一致性，
but not for multiple, on multiple objects.
但不是针对多个对象。
You have even multiple clients talking to this,
你有多个客户端访问这个，
you know are doing operations on the same object,
在同一个对象上执行操作，
have strongly linearizability correct in this scheme,
在这个方案中，具有强一致性，
the question is,
问题是，
we have linearizability across objects too.
我们也可以有跨对象的线性一致性。
But, why is that important
但是，为什么这很重要，
and I don't see where like where that would be important like,
我没有看出，这在哪里是重要的，
because you, you gonna like, you can't group operations, right,
因为你，你不能对操作进行分组，
so like a write and a write.
就像一次写入和一次写入。
I mean you read object one,
我的意思是你读取对象一，
you write object one, you read object one,
你写入对象一，你读取对象一，
you read object two, you write object two,
你读取对象二，你写入对象二，
and you know the, the question is,
问题是，
you know in linearizability, you know those operations need to be total order,
在线性一致性中，这些操作需要是完全有序的，
and they need to preserve this property of real time.
它们需要保持这种属性的实时性。
And since you have different chains,
因为你有不同的链，
that might actually not happen,
这可能不会发生，
but I don't want to commit to,
但我不想承诺，
no [statement] about all across chains.
不确定关于所有链的[声明]。
You know with the chain is actually guaranteed to linearizability,
链保证了线性一致性，
even if you have different objects.
即使你有不同的对象。
There's something I don't understand in the paper,
在论文中，我有一些事情不明白，
which is the update propagation invariant,
就是更新传播不变量，
where like sort of the,
就像是，
for in this order of the chain.
在这个链的顺序中。
Yep.
是的。
The like commits are prefix of each successor's commits,
提交是每个后续提交的前缀，
is that guaranteed after like a full pass has gone through the chain?
这是不是保证[完整传递]通过链？
No, it's always true, right,
不，它总是真的，
like you know you go back to this picture here,
比如你再看这张图片，
I think they make a very simple observation,
我认为他们做了一个非常简单的观察，
which is, let's see if we can find that picture,
让我们看看，能不能找到那张图片，
I probably scribbled over everything,
我可能什么都胡乱写下来了，
so it's gonna be maybe not as clean,
所以它可能不是那么干净，
basically what they're saying,
基本上他们说的是，
like if you look at this figure, correct,
如果你看这个图，
that S3 always has a prefix of S2
S3 总是具有前缀 S2 ，
and S2 always has a prefix of S1,
并且 S2 总是具有前缀 S1 ，
and that's the only thing that basically that's invariant says.
这是唯一一件不变量的事情。
Oh, so i and j,
哦，那么 i 和 j ，
so the one out the successor has the prefix of the predecessor?
那么后继者的前缀是前缀吗？
Yeah, and this is slightly confusing,
是的，这有点让人困惑，
I just realized that later,
我后来才意识到，
after somebody else asked this question,
在别人问了这个问题之后，
in the definition, the i and j is in two different ways,
在定义中， i 和 j 是两种不同的方式，
well, not really different ways,
嗯，没有什么不同的方式，
one is definition,
一个是定义，
and one is actually the invariant,
一个是不变量，
and you're gonna be a little careful,
你要小心一点，
the role of i and j in the chain.
i 和 j 在链中的角色。
That sort of around.
这有点绕。
Yeah exactly.
是的，就是这样。
How is that possible.
这怎么可能。
Exactly.
没错。
Thank you.
谢谢。
You're welcome.
不用谢。
I was, oops.
我是，糟糕。
Yeah.
嗯。
I was just gonna ask,
我只是想问，
what happens when you have a network partition instead of crash,
当你有一个网络分区而不是崩溃时会发生什么，
so if you go to the crash slide,
如果看崩溃的幻灯片，
what happens to the chain,
链发生了什么，
if there's a network partition,
如果有网络分区，
so maybe ask something like,
所以也许可以问这样的问题，
like S2 is actually still alive,
比如 S2 实际上还活着，
but there's a partition between the configuration manager and S2 or something,
但是在配置管理器和 S2 或其他什么之间有一个分区，
and so now both S1 and S2 are pointing to S3.
所以现在 S1 和 S2 都指向 S3 。
No, no, yeah, yeah,
不，是的，
okay, there's gonna be some obviously,
好的，显然会有一些，
when I I think people are talking about this,
当我想人们在谈论这件事时，
but I presume that all configurations are numbered, like [] number
但我假设所有的配置都有编号，比如[]编号，
and S3 will not accept any commands from S2,
S3 不会接受任何来自 S2 的命令，
if the [] numbers don't match.
如果[]编号不匹配。
Oh, you got it, thank you.
哦，理解了，谢谢。
So related to that,
与这个有关，
one thing I couldn't figure out is,
我不能理解的一件事是，
even with like configuration numbers or something,
即使有类似的配置编号或其他东西，
how do you make sure that when you get rid of the tail,
你如何确保当你丢失尾部时，
in like the third scenario you drawn,
就像你画的第三个场景，
when you get rid of the tail,
当你丢失尾部时，
that all the clients that might issue a read
可能所有发出读取命令的客户端
are aware that this old server no longer.
都知道这台旧服务器不再。
Clients, I think the way you would do is,
客户端，我认为你做的方式是，
that the configuration, when the client download the configuration from configuration manager,
当客户端从配置管理器下载配置时，
they also include the [] number
它们还包括[]编号，
and every operation includes the [] number
每个操作都包括[]编号，
and S3 will say hi, that's an old [] number,
S3 会说，这是一个旧的[]编号，
don't talk to.
不要访问。
I guess, when the clients talk the configurations over to get [] numbers,
我想，当客户端访问配置获得[]编号，
I'm going to start with is a client,
我首先从一个客户端开始，
that has an old.
它有一个老的。
You know, so for example, the S2 could just say retry
例如， S2 可以重试，
and the client then go back to the configuration server and reread the state.
然后客户端返回到配置服务器并重新读取状态。
I guess what I'm worried about is,
我想我担心的是，
like S3 has been network partitioned away from from the coordinator,
比如 S3 与协调器网络分区，
and so the coordinator gets rid of S3 from the tail
所以协调器从尾部去掉 S3 ，
and increase the version number,
并增加版本号，
but some client out there doesn't find out that the version numbers increase
但是有些客户端并没有发现版本号增加了，
and still think S3 is the tail,
并且仍然认为 S3 是尾部，
talks to S3 doesn't read,
访问 S3 不要读取，
meanwhile people are do write to S1 S2,
同时人们对 S1 S2 进行写入，
and they have haven't seen that basically.
它们还没有看到这个。
Yeah, this is probably the reason why the paper go through the proxy.
是的，这可能就是为什么论文中通过代理。
I see, okay.
我明白了，好的。
I have a question kind of going back to that,
我有一个问题，回到那个问题上来，
like unanswered questions about,
没有回答的问题，
kind of like cross object linearizability,
比如跨对象线性一致性，
I guess like,
我想，
is that a whole other can of [] that we haven't really talked about,
这是不是[]我们还没有谈论过的，
which is like if you want to do,
如果你想做的话，
I don't know what the right term is,
我不知道什么是正确的术语，
but like transactions, that like cross multiple pieces of state,
但是比如事务，跨多个部分状态，
like, if you're trying to implement an operation,
例如，如果尝试实现一项操作，
where it's like you're setting a to 1 and b to 2
你把 a 设置为 1 ， b 设置为 2 ，
and you should only see those together or not at all,
你应该一起看到它们，或者根本看不到，
like [] of that,
就像[]那样，
have we talked about that in any of the things we've seen before.
我们有没有讨论过在以前见过的任何东西。
No and we'll talk about a couple weeks,
不，我们会在后面几个星期讨论，
it going to be a big topic,
这将是一个大话题，
basically how to do transactions.
就是怎么做事务。
Okay, that's good to know, thanks.
好的，很高兴知道，谢谢。
You mind going back to like the third slide?
你可以回去看第三张幻灯片吗？
Yep.
是的。
I can go to the third slide,
我可以去看第三张幻灯片，
maybe not, fourth slide,
也许不是，第四张幻灯片，
oh, it's fifth slide, sorry,
哦，是第五张幻灯片，抱歉，
so I was a little bit confused,
所以我有点困惑，
when you mention like if lock holder failed intermediate stage stuff,
你提到，如果锁持有者在中间状态失败，
what exactly on this slide applies to zlocks,
这张幻灯片上的哪些内容适用于 zlock ，
and what applies to the Go locks again.
哪些适用于 Go 锁。
The these almost all statements about zlocks.
这些几乎都是关于 zlock 的语句。
So is the first statement, that if the lock holder fails,
所以是否第一个语句，如果锁持有者失败，
then the intermediate state is not cleaned up, or is cleaned up.
那么中间状态不被清除，或者被清除。
No, intermediate state is visible,
不，中间状态是可见的，
but then generally you have a leader election,
但如果你有一个领导者选举，
you could clean up the intermediate state,
你可以清理中间状态，
that was just like the point.
这就是重点所在。
Oh, so with with Go locks,
哦，所以有了 Go 锁，
is that also not the case
难道不也是这样吗，
like if there's a machine that's holding a Go lock,
例如，如果有一台机器持有 Go 锁，
that's doing stuff,
它正在做一些事情，
and then all of sudden dies,
然后所有突然宕机，
isn't still the intermediate state visible.
中间状态是否仍然可见。
Okay, I I think what I'm talking about Go locks,
好的，我想我说的 Go 锁，
you know is something that's a statement about multiple threads
是一个关于多个线程的语句，
running on the same machine, right,
在同一台计算机上运行，
and so if the Go lock disappears,
所以如果 Go 锁消失了，
because machine crashes,
因为机器崩溃了，
all the threads on that machine crash too.
那台机器上的所有线程也会崩溃。
Right, but, when you say that the intermediate state is visible to other people,
是的，但是，当你说中间状态对其他人是可见的，
that's still true for Go locks, right.
这对于 Go 锁来说，仍然是正确的。
You know if they written persistent state to disk,
如果它们将持久状态写入磁盘，
or into some shared file system,
或某个共享文件系统，
like no, the machine is gone,
不，机器已经不在了，
the disk is gone, everything is gone.
磁盘不见了，一切都不见了。
Oh, got it, okay,
哦，知道了，好的，
so it's saying that,
所以这就是说，
the like the persistent, like intermediate state persistent.
比如中间状态持久化。
Zookeeper intermediate state might be visible,
zookeeper 中间状态可能是可见的，
we're gonna delete the guy might have created some more files
我们要删除可能创建了更多文件的，
and those are visible now.
这些都是可见的。
Okay I see, thank you.
好的，我明白了，谢谢。
So just follow that,
所以只是继续这个，
since the implementation that if a goroutine ever dies while holding the lock,
如果 goroutine 在持有锁的过程中死亡，
the entire Go program must have died too.
整个 Go 程序肯定也死了。
And as you can never have a goroutine die holding a lock with that,
你永远不会有持有锁的 goroutine 死亡，
and have other parts of the program continuously.
并继续其他部分的程序。
Okay.
好的。
The goroutine crashes, the application crashes.
goroutine 崩溃，应用程序崩溃。